<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
  <bookinfo>
    <orgname>Max Planck Institute for Psycholinguistics, Nijmegen, The Netherlands</orgname>
    <date>23 June 2012</date>
    <subtitle>Arbil</subtitle>
    <subtitle>for editing and managing IMDI metadata</subtitle>
    <releaseinfo>Arbil manual</releaseinfo>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/arbil-icon.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/logo.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <surname>George Saad, Anastasios Vogiatzis, Katarzyna Wojtylak</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
  </bookinfo>
  <chapter id="Ch_Introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>Arbil is an application for arranging research material and associated metadata into a
      format appropriate for archiving. </para>
    <para>Arbil is designed so that it can be used off line in remote locations. The data can be
      entered at any stage in part or as a whole. When an internet connection is available the work
      can then be transferred to the main archive via Lamus.</para>
    <section id="Sec_General_Information">
      <title>General Information</title>
      <para/>
      <para>Two steps are required in adding a corpus to the MPI Archive. The first involves
        creating the corpus, editing the metadata and converting it into an archivable format using
          <emphasis role="bold">ARBIL</emphasis>(Archive Builder) while the second involves
        exporting the created/edited corpus to the archive using <emphasis role="bold"
          >LAMUS</emphasis> .</para>
      <para>This manual describes in detail the first step i.e. <emphasis role="bold"
          >Arbil</emphasis>. For the second step, <emphasis role="bold">Lamus</emphasis>, please
        refer to the <ulink url="http://www.lat-mpi.eu/tools/lamus/">LAMUS manual</ulink>). </para>
      <para>The MPI Archive can ONLY accept corpora which are in the .IMDI format. By creating a
        corpus through Arbil, you create an IMDI file ready to be exported to the Archive. </para>
      <para> Arbil allows you to view all the corpora in the Archive or any other remote location
        (provided you have access rights).</para>
      <para>Corpora from the archive can also be edited through Arbil. If the changes are to be
        implemented they have to go through <emphasis role="bold">Lamus</emphasis>.</para>
      <para/>
      <para> In short, Arbil allows you to: </para>
      <para>1) View the Archive</para>
      <para>2) Import metadata from the Archive &amp; edit.</para>
      <para>3) Create new corpora, with new metadata and media files.</para>
      <para>4) Export the IMDI files, ready to be archived</para>
      <para/>
      <para>Changes you make to corpora imported from the Archive will <emphasis role="underline"
            ><emphasis role="bold">not</emphasis></emphasis> affect the Archive directly, as Arbil
        merely allows you to make changes on a <emphasis role="bold">local level</emphasis>, and not
        to the Archive itself. If you want to upload your changes to the archive, you must export
        them to LAMUS, which in turn, allows you to submit corpora into the archive.</para>
      <para>Arbil is the next generation of the <emphasis role="bold">IMDI</emphasis> Editor with a
        more powerful user interface and functionality. This manual contains detailed information on
        how to use Arbil: create new corpus structures/session nodes, and modify existing corpora.
        It does not explain the internal structure of IMDI (for more information on the IMDI
        metadata set, please see <ulink url="http://www.lat-mpi.eu/tools/imdi/">the LAT
          website</ulink>).</para>
      <para>For a less detailed program description, see the <ulink
          url="http://www.mpi.nl/corpus/html/arbil-imdi_ug/index.html">Arbil User
        Guide</ulink>.</para>
      <para>We encourage you to provide feedback, comments, and suggestions so that we can improve
        the documentation to better meet your needs. Also, in case of problems that are not
        addressed anywhere in this guide, please use the <ulink
          url="http://tla.mpi.nl/tools/tla-tools/arbil">Arbil Forum</ulink>.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="Sec_Overview">
      <title>Overview</title>
      <para>The way you start working on your data is twofold: </para>
      <para>a) you either create a new corpus or </para>
      <para>b) make a copy of an already existing corpus or its branch from the server and edit it.
        Either way, the files you create/edit will be saved on your computer (in the so called
          <emphasis role="bold">Local Corpus</emphasis>). This enables you to work off-line in
        remote locations while still in the field. Changes you make in Arbil will <emphasis
          role="underline">not</emphasis> affect the archive.</para>
      <para>Arbil consists of 6 working areas as shown in the figure below:</para>
      <para>- 1) <emphasis role="bold">The Menu Bar</emphasis> allows you to access the main
        commands </para>
      <para>- 2) <emphasis role="bold">The</emphasis>
        <link linkend="Sec_Remote_Corpus"><emphasis role="bold">Remote Corpus</emphasis></link>
        contains locations from the Language Archive. This is where you can view corpora and choose
        to import.</para>
      <para>- 3) <emphasis role="bold">The</emphasis>
        <link linkend="Sec_Local_Corpus"><emphasis role="bold">Local Corpus</emphasis></link>
        contains the user's main working area. This is where corpora from the Remote Corpus can be
        imported and edited. It's also used for creating new corpora.</para>
      <para>- 4) <emphasis role="bold">The</emphasis>
        <link linkend="Sec_Working_Directories"><emphasis role="bold">Files /Favourites (Working
            Directories)</emphasis></link>. This is where you can link directories from your
        computer to Arbil in order to import media files and create favourite metadata items.</para>
      <para>- 5) <emphasis role="bold">The Preview Area </emphasis>shows metadata of the selected
        node (In the figure below, it displays the details for "New Corpus"). It changes every time
        a new node is selected.</para>
      <para>- 6) <emphasis role="bold">The Table Area</emphasis> is where several nodes can be
        opened, compared, and modified at the same time (In the figure below, the three nodes from
        the Local Corpus are placed in a table in this area)</para>
      <para>Note: You can customise the size of these panes. To make a window larger or smaller
        place the pointer on the border and drag it in the direction in which you want the window to
        expand or contract. It is also possible to hide the preview area by unchecking the <emphasis
          role="italic">show selection preview</emphasis> from the <emphasis role="italic"
          >options</emphasis> menu.</para>
      <figure>
        <title>Arbil workspace</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Working_Area.jpg" contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1"
              width="100%"/>
          </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>
    <section id="Sec_Work_Flow">
      <title>Work flow</title>
      <para>When working with Arbil, you have to decide whether you are going to <link
          linkend="Sec_Remote_Corpus" role="bold">work on an existing corpus from the Remote
          Corpus</link> or <link linkend="Sec_New_Corpora" role="bold">create a new corpus</link>.
        Assuming that you intend to edit metadata in the Archive and add additional media files, you
        follow the steps 1-6 below. </para>
      <para>The Arbil work flow for editing a corpus is as follows:</para>
      <para>1) Browse the Remote Corpus and locate the corpus which you intend to edit; drag it from
        the Remote Corpus pane into the Local Corpus pane so as to import it. </para>
      <para>2) Now that the corpus is located in the Local Corpus, you may edit it freely. To edit
        the metadata, drag the node into the Table Area (6, image 1.1 ) and edit the fields
        accordingly (editing can also be done in an external editor). This can be done with several
        corpora/sessions at once.</para>
      <para>3) In order to add resources to sessions (e.g. media files and annotations), you must
          <link linkend="Sec_Working_Directories">set up a working directory</link> which links a
        folder on your computer to Arbil. This means that any media files in this folder will appear
        in the Working directory area so that <link linkend="Sec_Adding_Resource_Files" role="bold"
          >Resource files can be added</link> to the sessions of a corpus in your Local Corpus. To
        add files to your new corpus, drag and drop them from the <emphasis role="italic"
          >files</emphasis> to the <emphasis role="italic">local corpus </emphasis>. Now you can
        edit the metadata following step 2.</para>
      <para>4) Stored session elements, such as common actors, can be added to the local corpus from
        the <emphasis role="italic">favourites</emphasis>.</para>
      <para>5) Once your metadata have been edited correctly and your desired media files have been
        added to your sessions, you can export the metadata files to a directory (folder) on your
        computer.</para>
      <para>In order to create a new node, add a node in the Local Corpus and follow the same
        steps.</para>
      <para>Note: This is as far as you can get using Arbil. </para>
      <para>6) Once the work is finished, Open <ulink url="http://www.lat-mpi.eu/tools/lamus/"
          >Lamus</ulink> and import the directory (folder) which contains the corpora. It will then
        be <link lang="" linkend="Sec_Favourites">uploaded to the archive</link>.</para>
      <para>Corpus and session nodes are easily edited directly in Arbil (see <link
          linkend="Ch_Editing_Corpus_Structure">chapter 4</link> and <link
          linkend="Ch_Editing_Metadata">chapter 5</link>) but they can also be worked on in an <link
          linkend="Sec_Favourites">external editor</link> (such as Microsoft Excel or another
        spreadsheet program) see <link linkend="Sec_using_an_external_editor">7.3</link>. </para>
      <figure>
        <title>Arbil Work flow</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata contentdepth="100%" fileref="images/workflow.png" scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>In Arbil all work on corpora and sessions takes place in the Local Corpus tree. The
        various import, export, and edit operations displayed in the figure above, can usually be
        triggered by right-clicking on elements in the Local Corpus, or via "drag and drop" (e.g..
        clicking on an element in the Remote Corpus, holding the mouse key, and dragging the element
        to the Local Corpus, or to a corpus node within the Local Corpus). Media files (i. e. audio
        and video recordings) and written resources can also be added to sessions via "drag and
        drop" from the Working Directories tree in the Files tab. Only for importing previously
        exported sessions to the local corpus root one has to access the File menu in Arbil's menu
        bar. </para>
    </section>
    <section><title>Arbil icons</title><para>The following table defines graphical icons used by
        Abril:</para><para/><para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/top_node_icon.png"/> The top node
        of the Remote Corpus tree (read only) </para><para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/top_node_local_corpus_icon.png"/> The top node of the Local Corpus tree
        (contains local files) </para><para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/top_node_working_dir_icon.png"/> Top node of the Working Directories tree
        (short cuts of files in the Local Corpus) </para><para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/local_corpus_tree_icon.png"/> The file is in the Local Corpus  (local
        file) </para><para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/remote_server_icon.png"/> The file is on
        the remote server (read only) </para><para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/R%20n%20L.png"/>
          The file is located in the local corpus but has been imported from the remote
          server</para><para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/corpus_branch_icon.png"/> Corpus branch </para><para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/catalogue_icon.png"/>Catalogue</para><para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/session_icon.png"/> IMDI session</para><para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/right.png"/>Closed node (sub-components
        are folded)</para><para>
        <inlinegraphic fileref="images/down.png"/>Open node (direct sub-components are
        displayed</para><para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/imdi_contains_data.png"/> IMDI node that contains data </para>
      <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/imdi_contains_data.png"/><inlinegraphic
          fileref="images/unknown_type_archivable.png"/> Resource without specified resource
        link</para><para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/GreyDiamond.png"/>
        <inlinegraphic fileref="images/2.png" contentdepth="10"/> IMDI node with no data and the
        number of subnodes indicated.</para>
      <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/dataempty.png"/> Node has optional fields but contains no
        data</para><para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/written_resources_icon.png"/> Written resource </para><para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/video_resources_icon.png"/> Video resource </para><para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/audio_resources_icon.png"/> Audio resource </para><para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/image_resources_icon.png"/>Image resource </para><para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/lock.png" contentdepth="100%"/> Resource is locked and can only
        be opened by users with access rights.</para><para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/unlock.png" contentdepth="100%"/> Resource is unlocked for the
        user</para><para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/i.png"/>Info
          file</para><para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/unknown_type_archivable.png"/> In resources: archivable file of
        an unknown type</para><para><inlinegraphic contentdepth="100%" fileref="images/file.png"/> File that is not an archivable
        format and therefore cannot be added as a resource </para><para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/favourites_icon.png"/> The node has been added to the list of the
        favourites and can be duplicated via the favourites add menu </para><para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/loading01.png"/> Node is currently being loaded </para><para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/not_found_icon.png"/> File not
        found</para>
      <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/vocabulary_closed.png" align="left" contentdepth="80%"/>
        Cosed controlled vocabulary</para>
      <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/vocabulary_closed_list.png" contentdepth="13"/> Closed
        multiple vocabulary. Enter multiple values by inserting a comma (,) between separate
        entries.</para>
      <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/vocabulary_open.png" contentdepth="80%"/> Open controlled
        vocabulary (text can be selected from a list but new text can also be added)</para>
      <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/vocabulary_open_list.png" contentdepth="80%"/> Open
        multiple vocabulary by inserting a comma (,) between separate entries</para>
      <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/language1.png" align="left" contentdepth="100%"/>
        Language selection on field (e.g. Description language)</para><para/></section>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>Starting Arbil</title>
    <para>When you open Arbil for the first time the <emphasis role="italic">wizard</emphasis>
      appears and gives you the ability to configure Arbil to your needs. The first window is a
      welcome window, press <emphasis role="italic">next</emphasis> to move to the second step of
      the wizard. In this window you select the metadata format i.e. IMDI or CMDI; you can choose
      one of them or both. In this manual we will assume just IMDI. The third window gives you the
      ability to choose the corpora that will appear in the <emphasis role="italic">Remote
        corpus</emphasis> box. If you know the URL<footnote id="fn_url">
        <para>You can copy the URL of a corpus by selecting the node in the remote tree in Arbil
          when the wizard is not showing, right click and select 'Copy'; or get it from the IMDI
          browser by navigating to the corpus, right click the node and select 'Create bookmark' and
          copy the URL link. Then you can paste it into the box in the wizard.</para>
      </footnote> of a corpus that you will be working on frequently, you can add it to this list so
      that it will be available on the root level of the tree in the <emphasis role="italic">Remote
        corpus box</emphasis>. After finishing with <emphasis role="italic">Remote
        locations</emphasis> press <emphasis role="italic">next</emphasis> and then the <emphasis
        role="italic">finish</emphasis> button. You can reopen the wizard through the <emphasis
        role="italic">help</emphasis> menu by choosing <emphasis role="italic">Run setup
        wizard</emphasis>.</para>
    <para>
      <figure>
        <title>Welcome to Arbil </title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/welcome.png" contentwidth="50%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <figure>
        <title>Remote locations</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/wizard.png" contentwidth="50%" scale="1" width="50%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </para>
    <para>Starting Arbil can be done in two ways, either by webstart or by downloading the
      programme, see <ulink url="http://tla.mpi.nl/tools/tla-tools/arbil">here</ulink>. Note that
      webstart will not work for OpenJDK 7; in this case download the installer version.</para>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="Ch_Basics">
    <title>Set-up</title>
    <section id="Sec_Definitions">
      <title>Corpus nodes, sessions and catalogues</title>
      <para>It is important to understand the distinction between the following as these elements
        are essential to the internal structure of Arbil:</para>
      <para><emphasis role="italic">corpus node</emphasis>, <inlinegraphic fileref="images/corpus_branch_icon.png"/></para>
      <para><emphasis role="italic">corpus session</emphasis><inlinegraphic
          fileref="images/session_icon.png"/></para>
      <para><emphasis role="italic">corpus catalogue</emphasis>
        <inlinegraphic fileref="images/catalogue_icon.png" contentdepth="80%"/></para>
      <para>IMDI is organized hierarchically meaning that any number of other corpus nodes can fall
        under each <emphasis role="italic">corpus node</emphasis><inlinegraphic
          fileref="images/corpus_branch_icon.png"/> . These nodes do not describe resources but are
        meant to construct the corpus structure only. It is the<emphasis role="italic"> session
          nodes</emphasis><inlinegraphic fileref="images/session_icon.png"/> which include
        information about the actors, content, media file, project, source and written
        resources.</para>
      <para>A <emphasis role="italic">corpus catalogue,</emphasis><inlinegraphic
          fileref="images/catalogue_icon.png" contentdepth="80%"/> on the other hand, is a general
        descriptive element of the whole corpus. </para>
    </section>
    <section id="Sec_Remote_Corpus">
      <title>Remote Corpus</title>
      <para>The Remote Corpus contains all the corpora located in the archive. Currently it is not
        possible to <emphasis role="underline">add </emphasis>anything to the remote corpus or edit
        it in general. It is primarily used to view data and also allows you to import corpora to
        the Local corpus (discussed in <link linkend="Sec_Import_to_Local_Corpus">Section
        3.3</link>) where they can then be modified.</para>
      <para>It has a tree-like structure in which each node contains multiple sub-branches. To open
        any of them, click on the bullet to the left of the node representing the branch or double
        click the node itself. This can be repeated for the sub-branches as well. In this way you
        can view the whole structure of the corpus. If you click the bullet again, the node will
        fold back (the Remote Corpus is very similar in use to <ulink url="http://corpus1.mpi.nl/">
          the web-based IMDI browser</ulink>). </para>
      <section id="Sec_Adding_Removing_Remote_Locations">
        <title>Adding and removing Remote Locations</title>
        <para>If you want to use a corpus that is not available under remote corpus, or want to link
          it at root level, you can add it yourself, provided that you know the URL address of the
          corpus. Right click on the Remote Corpus top node and choose <emphasis role="italic">Add
            Remote Location</emphasis>. In the pop-up window enter the URL and press OK. The corpus
          should now appear in the main list of the Remote Corpus window.</para>
        <figure>
          <title>Adding a remote location</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
              <imagedata contentdepth="70%" fileref="images/Adding_a_remote_location.png"
                scalefit="1" width="70%"/>
            </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>Since you might not want to use all of the corpora in the Remote Corpus, it is also
          possible to remove any of the locations of the Remote Corpus at the root level so as to
          only display the corpora that you need. This can be done at the root level only (see
          figure 3.1) by right clicking on the node (e.g. for MPI corpora) and selecting <emphasis
            role="italic">Remove Remote Location</emphasis>.</para>
        <para/>
        <para>If you have removed some corpora, it is always possible to re-add them to the Remote
          Corpus by right clicking on it and selecting <emphasis role="italic">Add Default Remote
            Locations.</emphasis></para>
        <para>To add a subnode to the root level browse to the desired sub corpus, right click on it
          and choose <emphasis role="italic">Copy</emphasis>. Then go back to the top node of the
          Remote Corpus, right click on it, choose <emphasis role="italic">Add Remote
            Location</emphasis> and paste the URL in the dialogue box. The sub corpus will now
          appear in the Remote Corpus tree. </para>
        <para/>
        <para>The corpus data on the Remote Corpus are frequently updated by researchers. To be sure
          that you are working with the newest version of the available data, you can update it
          manually on the nodes that you believe have been altered. To do this, right click on the
          specific corpus/session you want to update and select <emphasis role="italic"
            >Reload</emphasis>. In principle, after new data has been entered into the archive, it
          can take up to an hour before the Archive is updated.</para>
      </section>
      <section id="Sec_Viewing_Corpus_Information">
        <title>Viewing Remote Corpus Information</title>
        <para>In general, the easiest way to view the information of a node is to drag and drop it
          from the remote corpus into the grey working area on the bottom right. It is also possible
          to right click on the selected node and choose<emphasis role="italic">View
            Selected</emphasis>. In either case, a window pops up with the desired information
          listed in tables. This can also enable you to view multiple nodes at the same time. </para>
        <para>To compare <emphasis role="italic">multiple</emphasis> nodes, simply hold Ctrl while
          clicking on the desired nodes. Then drag them to the working area (or right click and
          select <emphasis role="italic">View selected)</emphasis>. You will get a similar scenario
          to this displayed in the figure (3.2) below.</para>
        <para>Note: If you have an existing open table, it is also possible to add additional tree
          nodes of any form (i.e. sessions, corpora and files). Simply drag any unselected node from
          the tree structure and drop it on the table. It will be automatically added to the table
          as a row.</para>
        <para>
          <figure>
            <title>Viewing multiple selected corpora</title>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                <imagedata contentdepth="100%" fileref="images/viewing_selected_corpora.png" scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
              </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </para>
        <para>There are also two other quick ways for viewing  corpus/session information. </para>
        <para>(1) Let your cursor rest above a corpus or session node without clicking. Information
          about the corpus/session will be displayed in the tooltip under the cursor.</para>
        <para>(2) Click on a corpus/session node. Information will be shown up in the top right
          frame. </para>
        <para/>
        <para>When viewing information on multiple corpora, each row corresponds to one corpus,
          while each column corresponds to one metadata element (data category). By clicking on any
          of the column names, you can easily sort rows alphabetically within a given table.</para>
        <para/>
        <para>In a table that includes several different types of nodes (such as sessions and corpus
          nodes as listed in the table below) notice that not all the elements of the corpus
          structure are described in terms of the same data categories (column); for example, there
          are data categories that belong to a session but not to a corpus node. Such data fields
          are marked in grey and are not available this is also the case in the Local corpus (<link
            linkend="Sec_Local_Corpus">see Section 3.3</link>).</para>
        <figure>
          <title>Not editable cells in a table</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
              <imagedata contentdepth="100%" fileref="images/uneditable_fields.png" scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
            </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>In some cases you will see that instead of a value in a cell in the table there is a
          caption: &lt;multiple values>. This means that there is more than one value for this data
          category for this particular node. To see these values click on &lt;multiple values&gt;
          and a new window will pop up with the information shown.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section id="Sec_Local_Corpus">
      <title id="Sec_local_corpus" os="">Local Corpus</title>
      <para>The Local Corpus <inlinegraphic fileref="images/top_node_local_corpus_icon.png"
          contentdepth="70%"/> is located beneath the Remote Corpus pane in the Arbil left frame.
        Remember that the Local Corpus is the main working area and that changes made in the Local
        Corpus will not affect the Archive. The Local Corpus serves two main functions: 1) Edit
        existing corpora, 2) Creating new Corpora. Section 3.3.1 explains how local corpora may be
        modified by either (re)editing the data from the Remote Corpus. Section 3.3.2 explains how
        to create and subsequently modify new corpora, session nodes or resource files.</para>
      <section id="Sec_Import_to_Local_Corpus">
        <title>Import to Local Corpus</title>
        <para>If you have decided to work on a corpus from the Archive you first need to import it
          from the Remote Corpus to your Local Corpus, and then you can edit it. To do this, locate
          the node/session from the Remote Corpus and simply drag the item and drop it into the
          local corpus icon <inlinegraphic fileref="images/top_node_local_corpus_icon.png"
            scalefit="1" contentdepth="70%"/>. You can also right click on the corpus node you want
          to import and choose<emphasis role="italic"> Import to Local Corpus.</emphasis> In the
          dialogue box that pops up you can check the <emphasis role="italic">Show Details and
            Options</emphasis> box in order to: </para>
        <para>(1) <emphasis role="italic">Overwrite Local Changes</emphasis> : Overwrite an existing
          local corpus/session node from the same original location. When is this option useful?
          Consider the likely scenario that you have imported a node from the Remote corpus and
          started editing it. If you want to reset the changes, you can reimport it from the Remote
          Corpus and check the <emphasis role="italic">overwrite local changes </emphasis>box. You
          can apply this option to every branch of the corpora. To do so, first check<link
            linkend="image_overwrite_local_changes">Show details and options</link> box; in the
          window that appears select the function <link linkend="image_overwrite_local_changes"
            >Overwrite local changes</link>.</para>
        <figure>
          <title>Show details and options</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/ImportCata.png" contentdepth="40%"
                id="images_show_details_and_options"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <figure>
          <title>Overwrite local changes</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/ImportCata3.png" contentdepth="45%"
                id="image_overwrite_local_changes"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>In the case that you have uploaded a corpus from your local corpus to the Remote
          Corpus and you want to edit it again, editing should not be done in the already existing
          file in your Local Corpus. In this case you have to reimport the corpus from the Remote
          Corpus where your uploaded it before via Lamus.</para>
        <para>(2) <emphasis role="italic">Copy Resource Files</emphasis>: Import resource files to
          your computer. Please be aware that copying the resource files may take some time and will
          use disk space on your computer. When you press <emphasis role="italic">Start</emphasis>,
          the branch will be copied to your Local Corpus tree. The process can be interrupted by
          clicking <emphasis role="italic">Stop</emphasis>. Note that Arbil cannot deal with
          resources that need authentication.</para>
        <figure>
          <title>Importing a corpus branch to Local Corpus</title>
          <mediaobject><imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/Import_box.png" contentdepth="50%" scalefit="1" width="50%"
              />
            </imageobject></mediaobject>
          
        </figure>
      </section>
      <section id="Sec_New_Corpora">
        <title>Creating corpus and session nodes</title>
        <para>Instead of copying an existing corpus or corpus nodes from the Remote Corpus, you can
          also create your own corpus or add session nodes in the local corpus. Moreover, you can
          also add a catalogue in which the general information about your corpus will be
          stored.</para>
        <para>To do this, select the top node of the Local Corpus (corpus node), right click it and
          select the option <emphasis role="italic">Add > Catalogue, Add > Corpus</emphasis> or
            <emphasis role="italic">Add > Session.</emphasis> See <link
            linkend="Ch_Editing_Corpus_Structure">Chapter 4</link></para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section id="Sec_Working_Directories"><title>Working Directories</title><para>Beneath the Local Corpus window, you will find two different tabs: <emphasis role="italic"
          >Files</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">Favourites</emphasis>. This section
        describes <emphasis role="italic">Files</emphasis> and its <emphasis role="italic">Working
          Directories</emphasis> while <link linkend="Sec_Favourites">Section 3.5</link> focuses
          on<emphasis role="italic"> Favourites</emphasis>. This window is responsible for linking a
        folder from your computer to Arbil so that media files can be transferred into your corpus.
        It is advisable to have one or more folders on your computer that contains all the necessary
        files that you would like to upload to your corpus. This way, you can simply link this
        folder and retrieve all the necessary files.</para><para>The option <emphasis role="italic">Files</emphasis> is selected by default. Its <emphasis
          role="italic">Working Directories</emphasis> are meant to keep at hand the resources that
        you want to add to your corpus (such as annotations, audio files, pictures etc.). To add a
        new Working Directory, right click on the Working Directory node and select <emphasis
          role="italic">Add Working Directory</emphasis>. Now browse to the directory you want to
        add, select it and click <emphasis role="italic">Open</emphasis>. In the figure <link
          linkend="image_linked_folder">3.8</link>, the directory "Recursion pics" is about to be
        added to the Working directory, so as to access the media files present in this
        folder.</para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <title>Add working directories</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/WD1.png" contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>After linking a directory to Arbil, you will have access to the folder. To import the
        media files (e.g.. Droste.jpg) to a session of a corpus, simply drag and drop them into a
        session of a local corpus. </para>
      <para> </para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <title>Linked folder</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/WD2.png" contentdepth="55%" width="55%"
                id="image_linked_folder"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>Note: If you right click on Working Directories, you will also see that it is possible
        for Arbil to show you all hidden files (option <emphasis role="italic">Show hidden
          files</emphasis>). This option is useful when you want to include corpus files which are
        normally hidden in your file manager. </para>
      <para>Browsing through Working Directories is very similar to browsing through the Remote or
        the Local Corpus. To open/close a folder click on the bullet or double click on its name. If
        you have added or modified the content of a directory outside Arbil, by right clicking on
        the Working Directory, you can update its content in Arbil (the <emphasis role="italic">Reload</emphasis> option).</para>
      <para>Viewing file information is done in the same way as it has been described in Section
        3.2.2. (<link linkend="Sec_Viewing_Corpus_Information">Viewing Remote Corpus
          Information</link>). Remember that if you place the cursor over a file, an information
        window will appear that will give you a file description, including the information about
        whether the file is archivable or not. Archivable files can be uploaded to the server. Image
        3.7 shows an example of an archivable file: </para>
      <figure>
        <title>Archivable file</title>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo/>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata contentdepth="65%" fileref="images/archivable.png" scalefit="1" width="65%"
              />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>
      <para>Editable files from the Working Directory can also be opened by external applications.
        Right click a given file (e.g.. audio file, picture) and select <emphasis role="italic">Open
          in External Application</emphasis>.</para>
      <para>If the file is not archivable, the <inlinegraphic contentdepth="100%"
          fileref="images/file.png" width="2%"/> icon will appear. If you hold the mouse pointer on
        the file, you will see the following information:</para>
      <figure>
        <title>Unarchivable file</title>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo/>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata contentdepth="100%" fileref="images/unarchiveable.png" scalefit="1"
                width="100%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>
      <para>For the list of accepted file types and formats, check the <ulink
          url="http://www.mpi.nl/corpus/html/lamus/apa.html">LAMUS manual</ulink>. </para>
      <para>A file that is not supported by Arbil can be kept in Arbil and still be added to a
        Session, overriding the decision of the internal type checker. Right click on it and select
          <emphasis role="italic">Override Type Checker Decision</emphasis>, a pop up window will
        appear where you have to choose if this is a <emphasis role="italic">media file</emphasis>
        or a <emphasis role="italic">written resource</emphasis>; the <inlinegraphic
          contentdepth="100%" fileref="images/file.png" width="2%"/> will then change into an icon
        of either a Media file or a Written Resource file and can be added as a resource file. To
        open the file right click it again and select <emphasis role="italic">Open in External
          Application</emphasis>. Beware that overriding the type checker decision can cause your
        corpus not to be accepted into the archive (rejected by Lamus).</para>
    </section>
    <section id="Sec_Favourites">
      <title>Favourites</title>
      <para>The tab <emphasis role="italic">Favourites</emphasis> is meant for storing session
        elements that you would like to re-use in new sessions, such as <emphasis role="italic"
          >actor, language elements, location</emphasis> etc. Session elements that can be saved in
        Favourites are: IMDI sessions (<inlinegraphic fileref="images/session_icon.png"/>), actors,
        content elements etc). If you have a number of elements in your Favourite List and you are
        not certain what the content of a given element is, you can always place the cursor over it
        and wait for the tool tip (information window) to appear.</para>
      <figure>
        <title>Favourites List</title>
        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata contentdepth="100%" fileref="images/favourites.png" scalefit="1" width="50%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>
      <para>In order to add an element from the local corpus to the Favourites List, right click its
        node and choose <emphasis role="italic">Add to Favourites List.</emphasis> The element now
        appears in the Favourites List. You can also just drag them from the corpus tree structure,
        right down to the Favourites List. If this element is needed again, you can place it into a
        preferable location in your Local Corpus either by dragging it from the Favourites list or
        Copy/Paste it in one of the Local Corpus (sub)branches. <figure>
          <title>Adding to favourites via menu</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/adding_to_favourites.png" contentdepth="50%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure></para>
      <para>Once you have completed your Favourites list, you can start using it. Let's say you want
        to add a particular Actor to a session - in order to do this choose the session in question,
        right click it and choose Favourites, Add from Favourites and click on the right actor. You
        can also do this by "drag and drop".<figure>
          <title>Adding favourites to a Session</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/adding_from_favourites.png" contentdepth="50%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure></para>
      <para>Note that the items in the Favourite List can be viewed and edited in the same way as
        the elements of the Local Corpus (right click and View/Edit Selected). This means that if
        you make changes to your favourites you have to right click on them and select Save Changes
        to Disk to make them permanent (or use Ctrl/cmd+S). The favourites which have been edited
        turn in blue which indicates this element still has to be saved locally.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="Ch_Editing_Corpus_Structure">
    <title>Editing the corpus structure</title>
    <para>This chapter focuses on how to develop the structure of the Local Corpus.</para>
    <sect1 id="Sec_Adding_new_Node">
      <title>Adding a new corpus node</title>
      <para>Once you have created/imported a corpus, you can add new corpus branches to any corpus
        node of the Local Corpus. To do this, right click on a corpus node, scroll down to <emphasis
          role="italic">Add</emphasis> and choose <emphasis role="italic">Corpus</emphasis>. A new
        corpus (<emphasis role="italic">Standard Corpus</emphasis>) will be created in the tree
        structure directly under the node you clicked on. Notice that at the same time a window pops
        up, in which you can edit the metadata of the new corpus node (such as corpus name
        etc.).</para>
      <figure>
        <title>Adding a new corpus branch</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Add_corpus_node.png" contentdepth="50%" scalefit="1"
              width="50%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="Sec_Adding_Session_Node">
      <title>Adding a new session node </title>
      <para>In addition, a new session node can be added to each corpus node. Right click on a
        corpus node, scroll down to <emphasis role="italic">Add </emphasis>and select <emphasis
          role="italic">Session</emphasis> (figure 4.2). A new session will be created in the tree
        structure directly under the branch you have clicked on. Notice that at the same time a
        window pops up, in which you can again edit the metadata of that session. </para>
      <para>Remember that media files can only be added under Session nodes. For a more complete
        description on how to add media files to sessions, see <link
          linkend="Sec_Adding_Resource_Files">Section 4.7</link>. </para>
      <figure>
        <title>Adding a new session node to a corpus branch</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/addd_session.png" contentdepth="50%" scalefit="1" width="50%"
            />
          </imageobject>
         
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="Sec_Adding_Another_Description">
      <title> Adding a new catalogue node</title>
      <para>The catalogue node is generally meant to provide extensive information about the corpus
        and its sub-branches (remember that the metadata window of a regular corpus node only
        contains three fields to begin with). In this node you can insert various types of
        information about your (sub)corpora. It is available only for the corpus nodes, not the
        sessions. An example of all the fields contained in a catalogue is displayed below. It is
        highly advisable to create a catalogue for corpora! To add a new catalogue to a corpus
        branch, right click a corpus node, scroll down to <emphasis role="italic">Add</emphasis> and
        choose <emphasis role="italic">Catalogue</emphasis>. A catalogue will be created in the tree
        structure directly under the node.</para>
      <para/>
      <figure>
        <title>Catalogue</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/CatalogueSC.png" contentdepth="40%" scalefit="1" width="40%"
            />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para><emphasis role="underline"><emphasis role="bold">Note</emphasis>:</emphasis>A corpus
        node can only have one catalogue. If you already have a catalogue and decide to create a new
        one, your old one will be replaced by the new one.</para>
      </sect1>
    <sect1 id="Sec_Adding_Other_Components">
      <title>Adding other components</title>
      <para>As shown above, you can add session nodes and catalogues to corpus nodes. Moreover, you
        can also add additional elements to session nodes and catalogues. If you right click on a
        catalogue > add, you will see a list of items available in the context menu. Notice how some
        elements have the <inlinegraphic fileref="images/imdi_contains_data.png" contentdepth="50%"
        /> icon, whereas others have a icon<inlinegraphic fileref="images/new%20field.png"
          contentdepth="50%"/>. The <inlinegraphic fileref="images/imdi_contains_data.png"
          contentdepth="50%"/> icon represents a component that will be displayed in the hierarchy
        whereas the <inlinegraphic fileref="images/new%20field.png" contentdepth="50%"/> icon adds a
        new field (discussed below).</para>
      <figure>
        <title>Catalogue context menu</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/EditCATA.png" contentdepth="50%" scalefit="1" width="50%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="Sec_Adding_More_Descriptions">
      <title>Adding more field components</title>
      <para>Generally, every corpus/ session/ catalogue contains a particular set of fields which
        can be edited. Adding <inlinegraphic fileref="images/new%20field.png" contentdepth="50%"/>
        elements implies adding a new metadata field to the selected node.</para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <title>Standard field name</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/EditorCata.png" contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1"
                width="100%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>For example, the standard field name includes one field for author. You might want to
        add an additional 'author' field. To do this, right click on a catalogue, Add > (e.g..
        Author). Some fields can be added multiple times, others can be added only once.</para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <title>Add new metadata field</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/AddFieldCatalogue.png" contentdepth="40%" scalefit="1"
                width="40%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Add field with custom name</title>
      <para>In case you want to add a field with a custom name to a node in a session right click on
        the node name in the tree structure and select <emphasis role="italic">Actor Key</emphasis>
        (in the example of an actor node). The new field appears as <emphasis role="italic"
          >Keys.Key.Standard Template Key</emphasis> in the list of the field names. In order to
        change the name of this new field right click on it, choose <emphasis role="italic">Open in
          External Editor</emphasis> and right-click the <emphasis role="italic">Change key
          name</emphasis> button and then <emphasis role="italic">OK</emphasis>. After you have
        changed the name, click on <emphasis role="italic">Apply</emphasis> for the name to change.
        Note that the new name will always start with Keys.Key., which is there by default. Only
          <emphasis role="italic">key</emphasis> fields can have their name changed. Note that you
        can add a field with a custom name (<emphasis role="italic">key</emphasis> option) only in
          <emphasis role="italic">Session, Content, Actor, Media File, Written Resource and
          Source</emphasis>.</para>
      <para>After you have added and customized the new key field(s) and you wish to use it other
        nodes, you can create a favourite for this node so that you can re-use it instead of
        repeating the whole process for every new node.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="Sec_Adding_Resource_Files">
      <title>Adding resource files to a session</title>
      <para>There are two ways of adding resource files (e.g. audio, video etc.) to a
        session:</para>
      <para>(1) The easiest way is to drag and drop a given element from the Working Directory to a
        session node. All information about the resource (e.g.. its size, type etc.) will be filled
        in automatically.</para>
      <para>(2) It is also possible to add it by right clicking on a session node and choosing
          <emphasis role="italic">Add</emphasis> ><emphasis role="italic">Media File</emphasis> or
          <emphasis role="italic">Add</emphasis> > <emphasis role="italic">Written
          Resource</emphasis>. In the latter case however you will have to fill in manually the
        location of the file, its media type, format and size in the window that will appear.</para>
      <para>Note that not all file types are archivable. If a file is not archivable, you will not
        be able to drag and drop it (any problem with the file will be illustrated by the
          <inlinegraphic contentdepth="50%" fileref="images/file.png"/> icon).</para>
      <figure>
        <title>Adding a written resource by dragging and dropping</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Adding_a_written resource_by_dragging and_dropping.png"
              contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
          </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <figure>
        <title>Adding a media file via the menu</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Adding_a_media_file via_the_menu.png" contentdepth="100%"
              scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
          </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para/>
      <para>It is also possible to add resources, either from a remote location, i.e. the archive or
        the web, manually. This can be done by right clicking on a node that supports a resource
        location (IMDI media file or written resource) select "insert manual resource location" and
        add the URL in the window that appears.</para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <title>Insert  manual remote resources</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/add_remote_resources_manually.png" contentdepth="60%"
                scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="Sec_Moving_Sessions">
      <title>Moving corpus and session nodes</title>
      <para>Arbil allows to move both corpus and session nodes from one location to another. To do
        it, select in your Local Corpus a corpus/session you would like to move and drag and drop it
        to the new location. It is also possible to move subnodes of sessions, e.g. Actors, across
        sessions.</para>
      
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="Sec_Deleting_Corpus_Elements">
      <title>Deleting corpus elements</title>
      <para>In order to delete corpus branches, sessions or session components, right click on a
        chosen element and select <emphasis role="italic">Delete</emphasis>. If you want to remove
        several elements at a time, choose them all while holding the Ctrl (or Shift) button. Right
        click on the selected elements and chose <emphasis role="italic">Delete</emphasis>. In each
        case you will have to confirm the deletion.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Saving changes</title>
      <para>The changes to your files are not made automatically. You have to save them yourself. To
        save the changes made in your local corpus, right click on the node and choose <emphasis
          role="italic">Save Changes to Disk</emphasis> or use the key short cut (i.e.
        Ctrl+S/cmd+S).</para>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="Ch_Editing_Metadata">
    <title>Editing the metadata</title>
    <sect1 id="Sec_One_Cell_Editing">
      <title>Editing one cell</title>
      <para>To edit a corpus or session just click on it (A), or select it and choose <emphasis
          role="italic">view selected</emphasis> (B). In the window that appears, click on the field
        you want to change. Type in the new value and press <emphasis role="italic">Enter</emphasis>
        to go to the next value. If the value you have typed is too long for the cell, the <emphasis
          role="italic">long field editor</emphasis> will open automatically in order to edit this
          value.<link linkend="sec_Long_field_editor">section 5.2</link></para>
      <figure>
        <title>Editing</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/simple_editing.png" contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1"
              width="100%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>Some of the cells have either an open<inlinegraphic fileref="images/vocabulary_open.png"
          contentdepth="50%"/>,<inlinegraphic fileref="images/MCV.png" contentdepth="50%"/> or a
        closed <inlinegraphic fileref="images/vocabulary_closed.png" contentdepth="50%"/>,
          <inlinegraphic fileref="images/vocabulary_closed_list.png" contentdepth="50%"/>vocabulary
        (figure 5.2). In both cases when you double click the field you need, a drop-down menu will
        appear showing you available default values. In the case of open vocabulary fields, you are
        permitted to type your own value (if, for example, you would like to have "grandfather" as a
        family role but you cannot find it in the list). In closed vocabulary fields, however, it is
        only possible to choose from the list (e.g. sex: male/female). Notice that when you enter a
        value that is incorrect, the text will be shown in red; otherwise it is in blue. In the case
        of <inlinegraphic fileref="images/MCV.png" contentdepth="50%"/> you can add multiple values
        (either from the drop down, or your own) by inserting a comma (,) between the values (typing
        the first letter of the new value will offer a suggested value from the drop down). In
        controlled vocabulary fields 'type-ahead' functionality is available; to confirm a
        suggestion, press ENTER or type a comma in multi-CV to add another value.</para>
      <figure>
        <title>Closed vocabularies</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Closed_vocabularies.png" contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1"
              width="100%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>In some descriptive elements, you will also see a drop-down menu from which you can
        choose a language which you use to describe the data information. To do so, click in the
        right corner of the field.</para>
      <figure>
        <title>Choosing a language, click on desired language</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/description_and_select_language.png" contentdepth="100%"
              scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="sec_Long_field_editor">
      <title>Long field editor</title>
      <para>The Long Field Editor (LFE) allows the user to edit long values, such as descriptions.
        The LFE works either automatically or manually. In the case you want to add a long
        description in a cell you can right click on the field in the table and select <emphasis
          role="italic">Open in Long Field Editor</emphasis>. In the window that appears you can add
        and edit the text. In the case that a field already contains a long value and you wish to
        edit it, double click on it; the LFE will open automatically. </para>
      <para/>
      <para>The LFE can be opened on a selected node by right clicking on it and selecting <emphasis
          role="italic">View/Edit in Long Field Editor</emphasis>. The LFE opens on the first field
        under the node, you can then navigate in the fields by using the <emphasis role="italic"
          >previous</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">next</emphasis> buttons (1). The field
        you are currently in appears on the top of the LFE (2). The text appears and can be edited
        in the white area (3).</para>
      <para>Changes made in the LFE get applied to the field as soon as the LFE is closed or by
        pressing the <emphasis role="italic">previous</emphasis> or <emphasis role="italic"
          >next</emphasis> buttons.</para>
      <figure>
        <title>Long Field Editor</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/long_field_editor.png" contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1"
              width="100%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>      
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="Sec_Editing_Multiple_Cells">
      <title>Editing multiple cells</title>
      <para>It will often be the case that a piece of information (e.g.. continent, country, address
        etc.) has to be repeated across the sessions. Instead of typing this data in every session,
        you can copy-paste it at once into all the relevant fields. Choose the relevant sessions by
        holding Ctrl and clicking on them. Then right click one of the selected items and choose
          <emphasis role="italic">View/Edit</emphasis>. You will see a window appearing in which you
        can edit the sessions.</para>
      <para>To edit the selected sessions, take the following steps:</para>
      <para>1. Fill one of the session fields / choose a default value from the drop-down menu that
        you need (e.g. Country). If one of these session fields is already filled in with the
        relevant information, skip this step.</para>
      <para>2. Right click on one of the selected cell and select <emphasis role="italic"
          >Copy</emphasis>.</para>
      <para>3. Select the fields where you want to paste the copied information (one by one) by
        holding Ctrl and clicking on them. Right click on one of the selected fields and chose
          <emphasis role="italic">Paste</emphasis>.</para>
      <figure>
        <title>Pasting data into multiple cells</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Pasting_data_into multiple_cells.png" contentdepth="100%"
              scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>If you want to copy a value into <emphasis role="underline">all</emphasis> the cells of
        a certain column, select the field you want you copy, right click it and chose <emphasis
          role="italic">Copy Cell to Whole Column</emphasis>. All the cells in the column will be
        changed accordingly. Note, however, that this option is only applicable to one column at a
        time.</para>
      <para/>
      <figure>
        <title>Copying the value of a cell to all the cells of a column</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata contentdepth="100%" fileref="images/copy_to_whole_column1a.png" scalefit="1"
              width="100%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>It is also possible to simultaneously copy-paste values to multiple columns. To do that,
        while holding Ctrl (or cmd), select the relevant cells of a metadata file, right click one
        of them and choose <emphasis role="italic">Copy</emphasis>.</para>
      <figure>
        <title>Copying values from columns in one metadata file</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/coping_two_columns_a.png" contentdepth="40%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para/>
      <para>Now choose the cells within the selected columns in to which you want to paste the
        copied value by Ctrl (or cmd) clicking on them (you can also draw a box over them with the
        cursor), right click one of the cells and select <emphasis role="italic">Paste</emphasis>.
        The values will be pasted into the appropriate columns.</para>
      <para>Note that you cannot copy-paste data from different rows, only from different
        columns.</para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <title>Pasting values from two columns into several metadata files</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/pasting_two_columns2_a.png" contentdepth="70%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <sect2>
        <title><emphasis role="italic">Find</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic"
            >Replace</emphasis></title>
      <para>Another option in editing cells is the <emphasis role="italic">Find and
          Replace</emphasis> option activated by pressing CTRL+F when in a table, or by right
        clicking on a cell and selecting "Find/Replace". In this case a line appears at the bottom
        of the table with two boxes (figure 5.7); the left box is used to define the term you intend
        to find in order to replace. Replacing is not done by typing in each cell you intend to
        change, but by adding the new term in the right box. By pressing the <emphasis role="italic"
          >Find Next</emphasis> key the term specified in the first box is highlighted in the table,
        you can either change it by pressing the <emphasis role="italic">Replace Selected</emphasis>
        key, or skip it and move to the next by pressing <emphasis role="italic">Find
          Next</emphasis>. Once you have moved to the next term in the table, you cannot go to a
        previous. In that case you will have to select a previous cell to start from and continue
        searching.</para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <title>Find and Replace</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/find_and_replace.png" scalefit="1" contentdepth="100%"
                  width="100%"/>
              </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </para>
    </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Editing All Metadata of a Subnode </title>
      <para>It is also possible for the user of Arbil to get access to all metadata under a node in
        a hierarchical order (figure 5.10), as the order of the (sub)sessions, so as to edit them.
        To do this, right click on a session on the tree view and select "<emphasis role="italic"
          >edit all metadata</emphasis>" (this function cannot be used on Corpus nodes). Editing can
        be done in all cells in the way it has already been described.</para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <title>Edit/view all metadata</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/edit_all_metadata.png" contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1"
                width="100%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="Sec_Customizing_Column_Views">
      <title>Customizing Column Views</title>
      <para>When viewing/editing multiple elements in a table, sometimes there are a lot of columns
        to go through. It is possible to reduce them by choosing which columns you want to see or
        which columns you want to hide. Right click the header of any column i.e. "Name" and select
        the option <emphasis role="italic">Edit This Column View</emphasis>. In the window that pops
        up, you can select columns that you want to show <emphasis role="italic">(Show Only)
        </emphasis>or hide<emphasis role="italic"> (Hide)</emphasis> (if you check only the
          <emphasis role="italic">Hide</emphasis> column, the unchecked names will appear in the
        window). It is important to know that the column(s) which disappear from this particular
        window, are not removed from the corpus itself.</para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <title>Choosing columns</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/choose_collumns_a.png" contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1"
                width="100%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>So let's say that you have <emphasis role="italic">Date</emphasis> and <emphasis
          role="italic">Description</emphasis> marked as <emphasis role="italic">Show
          only</emphasis> (figure 5.12). This means that if you would now use this window to check
        out a node that has other categories than the ones selected with the option <emphasis
          role="italic">Show only</emphasis>, then these categories will not be displayed. So the
        window in this particular example will only have two columns.</para>
      <para>If you have a table with: Name, Title and Description and you set the Description to
        Hide, it means that Description will never be shown. But if the elements that you add to the
        window have other categories, these will still be displayed and the number of columns will
        increase accordingly (assuming that you don't use the show only option).</para>
      <para>One more option of customizing the column view is the function <emphasis role="italic"
          >Limit View to Current Columns</emphasis>, which you will find by right clicking the
        header of a column. When chosen, this mode will freeze the current columns view, meaning
        that no matter what element you add to the window, only the current categories (columns)
        will be shown.</para>
      <para>It is also possible to set the width of the columns by dragging the right or left edge
        of the column. This applies to arbitrary open tables as well as saved column views.</para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <title>Editing column view</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/editing-column-view.png" contentwidth="60%" scalefit="1"
                width="60%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>It is also possible to hide a column from the current view. To do this, right click the
        column that you do not want to be displayed and choose <emphasis role="italic">This
          column</emphasis> and then <emphasis role="italic">Hide Column</emphasis>. </para>
      <figure>
        <title>Hiding one column</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata contentdepth="100%" fileref="images/hide_one_collumn.png" scalefit="1"
              width="100%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>Once you have hidden the unnecessary columns, you can save this view by right clicking
        any of the headers of the columns and choosing<emphasis role="italic"> Save Current Column
          View</emphasis>. Give the column view a name and select <emphasis role="italic"
          >OK</emphasis>. </para>
      <figure>
        <title>Saving Column View</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata contentdepth="100%" fileref="images/saving_collumn_view.png" scalefit="1"
              width="100%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>Currently it is not possible to delete the column views that you create.</para>
      <para>The view you have just saved is also applicable to other tables. Right click the header
        column of the new Table, select <emphasis role="italic">Column View for this
          Table</emphasis> and choose the view you want. By default, there are two views already
        defined and cannot be modified: <emphasis role="underline">All</emphasis> (i.e. all columns
        are displayed), and <emphasis role="underline">Minimal</emphasis> (i.e. displaying only
          <emphasis role="italic">Name</emphasis>, <emphasis role="italic">Title</emphasis> and
          <emphasis role="italic">Description</emphasis>). It is important not to forget that each
        view you create initially is window specific. In this way you can use different views for
        different windows. </para>
      <para>It is also possible to set your modified column view as the default column view that
        will appear in all tables you open. To do this go to <emphasis role="italic"
          >options</emphasis> in Arbil toolbar, scroll to <emphasis role="italic">Column View For
          New Tables </emphasis>and then select the preferred column view. This is now your default
        column view. (figure 5.15/1).</para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <title>Setting new default column view</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/default_collumn view.png" contentdepth="50%" scalefit="1"
                width="50%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para/>
      <para>Note: Column views that have been modified and multiple open windows in the working
        area, either saved or unsaved, are available after closing Arbil once the programme starts
        again exactly in the same way they were before closing it provided the <emphasis
          role="italic">Save Windows on Exit</emphasis> is activated in the <emphasis role="italic"
          >Options</emphasis> menu (figure 5.15/2).</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="Sec_Highlighting_Cells">
      <title>Highlighting cells with the same value</title>
      <para>If you want to see, which cells in a table have the same value, right click the
        appropriate cell and choose <emphasis role="italic">Highlight Matching Cells.</emphasis>
        Cells with the same value will be highlighted. You can do this with more than one cell -
        each new group of matching cells will be given a different colour. To remove the highlight,
        right click on a cell and choose: <emphasis role="italic">Clear Cell Highlight</emphasis>,
        which is visible in the above figure as well.</para>
      <figure>
        <title>Highlighting cells</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata contentdepth="50%" fileref="images/highlighting_cells1.png" scalefit="1"
              width="100%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="Ch_Exploring">
    <title>Searching</title>
    <sect1 id="Sec_Searching">
      <title>Searching Local Corpus</title>
      <para>The search option allows you to find a value(s) throughout either the Local Corpus or
        the Remote Corpus (paragraph 6.2). To do that, right click on a given node you want to
        search in and select <emphasis role="italic">Search</emphasis> (you might also choose a
        number of nodes by holding Ctrl and clicking on them). A window will appear in which you can
        specify where exactly you want to search e.g. within Corpus, Session, Catalogue, Actor
        etc.</para>
      <figure>
        <title>Selecting search locations</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
            <imagedata contentdepth="100%" fileref="images/searching.png" scalefit="1" width="90%"/>
          </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      
      <para>In the search window you can further specify in which column you want to search. By
        clicking on <emphasis role="italic">column</emphasis> a drop down list appears which
        contains pre-defined common values and previously entered column names; it is also possible
        to add any column name to this list, or remove arbitrary items by selecting the value and
        pressing <emphasis role="italic">shift</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic"
          >delete</emphasis>; deleted values again have to be retyped and searched for in order to
        appear in the drop down list again. After specifying the column (i.e. Name), give the value
        name you look for, e.g. "Blance", and click on <emphasis role="italic"
        >Search</emphasis>.</para>
      
      <para>By selecting either <emphasis role="italic">Equal</emphasis> (<inlinegraphic
          fileref="images/Equal.jpeg" contentdepth="50%"/>) or <emphasis role="italic"
          >Unequal</emphasis> (<inlinegraphic fileref="images/Unequal.jpg" contentdepth="50%"/>),
        you will need to specify whether your search results should match the word you filled in or
        rather show you where this word does not appear.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Searching Remote Corpus</title>
      <para>In the first row of the remote search it is necessary to specify what you are looking
        for in the remote corpus so that the search will be narrowed down within the remote corpus
        (figure 6.2). The results based on the first row provide all the nodes from all the sessions
        with this term (green box below). These results can be reduced by specifying more values in
        the second search row (red box). After specifying values in the second line searching in the
        remote corpus is similar to searching in the local corpus.</para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <title>Searching Remote Corpus</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/searching_remote_corpus.png" contentdepth="43%"
                scalefit="1"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para/>
    </sect1></chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>Exporting and Importing data</title>
  
  
    <sect1 id="Exporting_data_from_Arbil">
      <title>Exporting data from Arbil</title>
      <para>After creating new corpus branches or editing corpora from an already existing archive,
        you can save your files and upload them to the appropriate archive. In order to do this you
        need to export your files from Arbil. To do this select the modified nodes or a branch that
        contains the modified parts, right click them and select <emphasis role="italic">Export</emphasis>. A dialogue box will pop up, in which you choose the location of the
        export and the name of the file. To complete the export, click on <emphasis role="italic">Export Branch Destination Directory</emphasis>.</para>
      <figure>
        <title>Exporting files</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
            <imagedata contentdepth="50%" fileref="images/exporting files.png" scalefit="1"
              width="50%"/>
          </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>The following message will appear:</para>
      <figure>
        <title>Export alert message</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
            <imagedata contentdepth="100%" fileref="images/exporting_branch_details.png" scalefit="1" width="40%"/>
          </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>Selecting <emphasis role="italic">OK</emphasis> will lead you to a new message window
        where, before clicking on <emphasis role="italic">Start</emphasis>, you can chose the option
          <emphasis role="italic">Show Details and Options</emphasis>:</para>
      <figure>
        <title>Export window with details</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
            <imagedata contentdepth="40%" fileref="images/exporting_details1.png" scalefit="1"
              width="40%"/>
          </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>The options <emphasis role="italic">Rename Metadata Files</emphasis> and <emphasis
          role="italic">Limit Characters in File Names </emphasis>are already checked. The option
          <emphasis role="italic">Copy Resource Files</emphasis> are explained in the <link
          linkend="Sec_Import_to_Local_Corpus">import to Local Corpus section</link> (3.3.1).</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Importing data into Arbil</title>
      <para>In Arbil there is a number of possibilities to import the data. The first way to import
        data is from the Remote corpus to the Local corpus by right clicking on the remote corpus
        and selecting import to local corpus, or by "drag and drop". </para>
      <para>In the case you want to import data from you local computer disk, or the network, you
        can do this from the  menu bar by going to <emphasis role="italic">Files</emphasis>,
          <emphasis role="italic">Import</emphasis> and then selecting the data from your local
        disk, or the network; your data is imported at the root level. </para>
      <para><emphasis role="italic">Import Branch</emphasis> (i.e.. importing a piece of your
        corpus) gives you the ability to import part of your corpus from your disk to the Local
        corpus. <emphasis role="italic">Reimport</emphasis> (i.e.. re-importing form the remote
        corpus): in order to make changes to a corpus you have already exported to the Remote corpus
        via Lamus it is essential to reimport it to the Local corpus and select <emphasis
          role="italic">overwrite changes</emphasis>. </para>
      <para><emphasis role="italic">Import CSV</emphasis> (i.e. in the table format) gives you the
        ability to import edited data in the Local corpus in the form of a table (for details see
        section <link linkend="Sec_using_an_external_editor">7.3</link> below).</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title id="Sec_using_an_external_editor">Using an External Editor</title>
      <para>As has been noted already, it is possible to open, view and modify the data using
        external editors such as spread sheets or text editors. Overall the process is done by
        moving data from Arbil to the external editor, making the necessary changes, and then moving
        them back to Arbil. </para>
      <para>Moving data back to Arbil however posses some restrictions; for example, if you copy
        multiple rows in a table, the data format cannot be pasted back into Arbil. However it can
        still be viewed and edited in an external editor. For this reason after editing data in an
        external editor, such as Microsoft Excel, you can save you your data in csv format, and then
        import them to Arbil by right clicking on the preferred node and selecting <emphasis
          role="italic">import CSV</emphasis>. This way gives you the ability to import the data in
        a table format; in any other case you will have to import the edited data column by column,
        but not all at once.</para>
      <para>If cells in a table corresponding to a single metadata file are copied, then the data
        will be in a format that can then be pasted back into any table in Arbil, provided that the
        data maintains the same formatting.</para>
      <para>To open data in an external editor i.e. Ms Excel, select and copy the data from the
        table , then paste them in the editor you wish to use.</para>
      <figure>
        <title>Editing data in an External editor</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata contentdepth="100%" fileref="images/external-editor.png" scalefit="1"
              width="100%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>External application</title>
      <para>By selecting <emphasis role="italic">Open in External Application</emphasis> you can
        view, and edit, resourses and metadata in the application that your computer chooses by
        default, such as a media player for a video file, or a text editor for a text file.</para>
      <figure>
        <title>Viewing data in external application</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/exploring_viewing_data_otherwise1.png" contentdepth="38%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect1></chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>Exiting Arbil</title>
    <para>Before exiting Arbil make sure that you have saved all your changes. This can easily be
      done by the key short-cut CTRL+S.</para>
    <para>You can exit Arbil by closing the main window, or through file -> exit on Windows or
      Linux, or Arbil -> <emphasis role="italic">quit Arbil </emphasis>on Mac OS. In case of unsaved
      changes a message will appear and ask if you wish to <emphasis role="italic">save changes
        before exiting</emphasis>; choose <emphasis role="italic">yes</emphasis> or <emphasis
        role="italic">no</emphasis>, Arbil is now closed.</para>
    <para> </para>
  </chapter>
    <chapter>
    <title>Shortcut Keys</title>
    <para>In Arbil you can use the following shortcuts:</para>
    <table>
      <title>General shortcut keys</title>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>CTRL/CMD+A</entry>
            <entry>Select all</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>CTRL/CMD+F</entry>
            <entry>Find &amp; Replace </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>CTRL/CMD+S</entry>
            <entry>Save</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>CTRL/CMD+W</entry>
            <entry>Close topmost window</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>CTRL/CMD+SHIFT+W</entry>
            <entry>Close all windows</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>CTRL+TAB</entry>
            <entry>Next window</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>CTRL/CMD+SHIFT+TAB</entry>
            <entry>Previous window</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>CTR+P</entry>
            <entry>Hide/Show the selection preview</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>ENTER (in the tree)</entry>
            <entry>Open the current tree selection in a table</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>DELETE (in the tree)</entry>
            <entry>Delete the selected node from the tree</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <table>
      <title>Table short cut keys</title>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>CTRL/CMD+A</entry>
            <entry>Select all</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>CTRL/CMD+C</entry>
            <entry>Copy</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>CTRL/CMD+V</entry>
            <entry>Paste</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>CTRL/CMD+Z</entry>
            <entry>Undo</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>DELETE</entry>
            <entry>Delete the contents of the current table cell and start editing</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>ESC</entry>
            <entry>Cancel editing of the current cell</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>CTRL+ENTER</entry>
            <entry>Edit a cell in a new window</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
      <table>
        <title>Tree short cut keys</title>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>DELETE</entry>
              <entry>Delete the selected node in the tree</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <table>
        <title>Long field editor short cut keys</title>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>CTRL+UP</entry>
              <entry>Go to previous field</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>CTRL+DOWN</entry>
              <entry>Go the next field</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>CTRL+LEFT</entry>
              <entry>Go to previous tab</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>CTRL+RIGHT</entry>
              <entry>Go to next tab</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
  </chapter>
  <chapter role="application-help-only">
    <title>Technical details</title>
    <section>
      <title>Custom Filetypes Configuration</title>
      <para>It is possible to override the default set of filetypes that the type checker should recognize as archivable resources.</para>
      <para>To do so, place your custom filetypes.txt configuration file in the root of your local storage directory (to find out what that is, select Local Corpus Storage Directory from the Options menu). It will then automatically be installed in the type checker as soon as type checking takes place for the first time during a session. You will need to restart Arbil if it is already running.</para>      
      <para>For information about obtaining or creating a custom filetypes configuration, please contact your administrator.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Templates</title>
      <para>Templates are currently in development, but they will be used to customise the components added via the "Add" menu.</para>
      <para>To create a new template, create a directory in the ".arbil/templates" directory. This is where all the files relevant to that template will be stored. This directory will now be selectable via the "options/templates" menu.</para>
      <para>Each template can have its own XSL which is used via the "view formatted" menu. The XSL must be in the selected templates directory and be called "format.xsl". For example: .arbil/templates/{template name}/format.xsl. If there are any additional files required by the XSL they can be placed in the same directory as the XSL file.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
</book>
