<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
  <title>Arbil</title>
  <subtitle>Arbil 2.6, for editing and managing CMDI metadata</subtitle>
  <bookinfo>
    <orgname>The Language Archive, MPI for Psycholinguistics, Nijmegen, The Netherlands</orgname>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/arbil-icon.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/Clarin_logo2.png" contentwidth="45%"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    <releaseinfo>This manual was last updated in November 2015</releaseinfo>
    <releaseinfo>The latest version can be found at: <ulink
        url="http://http://tla.mpi.nl/tools/tla-tools/arbil/"
        >http://http://tla.mpi.nl/tools/tla-tools/arbil/</ulink></releaseinfo>
    <releaseinfo>Anastasios Vogiatzis (June 2012)</releaseinfo>
    <releaseinfo>Claudia Zabeo (December 2012)</releaseinfo>
    <releaseinfo>Janna Voelpel (September 2013)</releaseinfo>
    <releaseinfo>Francesca Bechis (July 2014)</releaseinfo>
    <releaseinfo>Steffen Kaiser (November 2015)</releaseinfo>
  </bookinfo>
  <chapter id="Ch_Introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>Arbil is an application for arranging research material and associated metadata into a
      format appropriate for archiving. Arbil is designed so that it can be used off line in remote
      locations. The data can be entered at any stage in part or as a whole. </para>
    <section id="Sec_General_Information">
      <title>General Information</title>
      <para>This version of Arbil manual focuses on creating collections of CMDI instances. These
        can be edited and converted into an archivable format to be exported on your local disk or
        to be submitted to a metadata repository. CMDI instances mainly consist of profiles and
        components.</para>
      <para>Besides creating collections of CMDI instances, Arbil allows you to view all the
        collections in the archive, or any other remote location (provided that you have access
        rights), as well as to edit collections from a remote location. </para>
      <para> In short, Arbil allows you to: </para>
      <para>1) View remote locations;</para>
      <para>2) Import metadata from the archive and edit them;</para>
      <para>3) Create new collections, with new metadata and media files;</para>
      <para>4) Export the CMDI files, ready to be archived.</para>
      <para>Changes you make to remote metadata will <emphasis role="underline"><emphasis
            role="bold">not</emphasis></emphasis> affect them directly, as Arbil merely allows you
        to make changes on a <emphasis role="bold">local level</emphasis>, and not on a remote
        level. </para>
      <para>Arbil is the next generation of the metadata editor, with more powerful user interface
        and functionality. This manual contains detailed information on how to use Arbil in order to
        create new collections of CMDI instances and modify existing ones. It does not explain the
        internal structure of CMDI (for more information on the CMDI metadata, please see the <ulink
          url="http://www.clarin.eu/cmdi">Clarin website</ulink>).</para>
      <para>For a less detailed program description, see the <ulink
          url="http://tla.mpi.nl/tools/tla-tools/arbil">Arbil User Guide</ulink>. </para>
      <para>You can access all the information present in this manual from the application itself,
        using the <emphasis role="bold">Help Menu</emphasis>. </para>
      <para>We encourage you to provide feedback, comments, and suggestions so that we can improve
        the documentation to better meet your needs. Also, in case of problems that are not
        addressed anywhere in this guide, please use the <ulink
          url="http://tla.mpi.nl/forums/software/arbil/">Arbil Forum</ulink>.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="Sec_Overview">
      <title>Overview</title>
      <para>The way you start working on your data is two-fold: </para>
      <para>a) either you create a new collection of CMDI instances </para>
      <para>b) or you make a copy of an already existing collection from a server and edit it. </para>
      <para>Either way, the files you create/edit will be saved on your computer (in the so called
          <emphasis role="bold">Local Corpus</emphasis>). This enables you to work off-line in
        remote locations while still in the field. Changes you make in Arbil will <emphasis
          role="underline">not</emphasis> affect the remote metadata.</para>
      <para>Arbil consists of 6 working areas as shown in the figure below:</para>
      <para>1) <emphasis role="bold">The Menu Bar</emphasis> allows you to access the main
        commands;</para>
      <para>2) The <link linkend="Sec_Remote_Corpus"><emphasis role="bold">Remote
          Corpus</emphasis></link> contains locations from the Language Archive. This is where you
        can view remote metadata and choose to import;</para>
      <para>3) The <link linkend="Sec_Local_Corpus"><emphasis role="bold">Local
          Corpus</emphasis></link> contains the user's main working area. This is where collections
        from the Remote Corpus can be imported and edited. It is also used for creating new
        collections;</para>
      <para>4) The <link linkend="Sec_Working_Directories"><emphasis role="bold">Files /Favourites
            (Working Directories)</emphasis></link>. This is where you can link directories from
        your computer to Arbil in order to import media files and create favourite metadata
        items;</para>
      <para>5) The <emphasis role="bold">Preview Area</emphasis> shows metadata of the selected node
        (in the figure below, it displays the details for "New Corpus"). It changes every time a new
        node is selected;</para>
      <para>6) The <emphasis role="bold">Table Area</emphasis> is where several nodes can be opened,
        compared, and modified at the same time (in the figure below, the four nodes from the Local
        Corpus are placed in a table in this area).</para>
      <para>
        <note>
          <para>You can customise the size of these panels. To make a window larger or smaller place
            the pointer on the border and drag it in the direction in which you want the window to
            expand or contract. It is also possible to hide the preview area by unchecking <emphasis
              role="bold">Show selection preview</emphasis> from the <emphasis role="bold"
              >Options</emphasis> menu.</para>
        </note>
      </para>
      <figure>
        <title>Arbil workspace</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/cmdi_Arbil_workspace.png" contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1"
              width="70%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>
    <section id="Sec_Work_Flow">
      <title>Work flow</title>
      <para>When working with Arbil, you have to decide whether you are going to <link
          linkend="Sec_Remote_Corpus" role="bold">work on an existing collection of instances from
          the Remote Corpus</link> or <link linkend="Sec_New_Corpora" role="bold">create a new
          collection of instances</link>. Assuming that you intend to edit metadata from a remote
        location and add additional media files, you will have to follow steps 1-6 below. </para>
      <para>The Arbil work flow for editing a collection of CMDI instances functions as
        follows:</para>
      <para>1) Browse the Remote Corpus and locate the metadata which you intend to edit; drag the
        metadata from the Remote Corpus panel into the Local Corpus panel so as to import them. </para>
      <para>2) Now that the remote metadata are located in the Local Corpus, you may edit them
        freely. To edit the metadata, drag the node into the Table Area (see figure 1.1 above, tab
        number 6) and edit the fields accordingly. This can be done with several nodes at
        once.</para>
      <para>3) In order to add resources to profiles (e.g. media files and annotations), you must
          <link linkend="Sec_Working_Directories">set up a working directory</link> which links a
        folder located on your computer to Arbil. This means that any media files in this folder
        will appear in the Working Directory area so that <link linkend="Sec_Adding_Resource_Files"
          role="bold">Resource files can be added</link> to the nodes in your Local Corpus. To add
        files to your new collection, drag and drop them from the <emphasis role="bold"
          >Files</emphasis> tab to the <emphasis role="bold">Local Corpus</emphasis>. Now you can
        edit the metadata following step 2.</para>
      <para>4) Stored profile components, such as common actors, can be added to the local corpus
        from the Favourites (either via drag and drop, or via the option <emphasis role="bold">Add
          from favorites</emphasis> that you find when right clicking the node in the Local Corpus
        where you want the favorites to be added.</para>
      <para>5) Once your metadata have been edited correctly and your desired media files have been
        added, you can export the metadata files to a directory (folder) on your computer, ready to
        be uploaded to a metadata repository.</para>
      <para>6) Finally, you can decide to make your metadata public. The procedure for this depends
        on the institution.</para>
      <figure>
        <title>Arbil Work flow </title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata contentdepth="60%" fileref="images/cmdi_Arbil_Workflow.png" scalefit="1"
              width="100%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>In Arbil all work on metadata takes place in the Local Corpus tree. The various
        operations displayed in the figure above can usually be triggered by right-clicking on
        elements in the Local Corpus, or via "drag and drop" (e.g. clicking on an element in the
        Remote Corpus, holding the mouse key, and dragging the element to the Local Corpus, or to a
        node within the Local Corpus). Media files (i. e. audio and video recordings) and written
        resources can also be added to nodes via "drag and drop" from the Working Directories tree
        in the Files tab. Only for importing metadata files from the file system (e.g. previously
        exported metadata) to the Local Corpus root, you have to access the File menu in Arbil's
        menu bar. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Arbil icons</title>
      <para>The following table defines graphical icons used by Abril:</para>
      <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/clarinE.png"/> CMDI metadata</para>
      <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/attribute.png"/>Attribute </para>
      <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/top_node_icon.png"/> The top node of the Remote Corpus
        tree (read only) </para>
      <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/top_node_local_corpus_icon.png"/> The top node of the
        Local Corpus tree (contains local files) </para>
      <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/top_node_working_dir_icon.png"/> Top node of the Working
        Directories tree (short cuts of files in the Local Corpus) </para>
      <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/local_corpus_tree_icon.png"/> The file is in the Local
        Corpus (local file) </para>
      <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/remote_server_icon.png"/> The file is on the remote
        server (read only) </para>
      <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/R_n_L.png"/> The file is located in the local corpus but
        has been imported from the remote server</para>
      <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/right.png"/>Closed node (sub-components are
        folded)</para>
      <para>
        <inlinegraphic fileref="images/down.png"/>Open node (direct sub-components are
        displayed</para>
      <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/imdi_contains_data.png"/> node that contains data </para>
      <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/imdi_contains_data.png"/><inlinegraphic
          fileref="images/unknown_type_archivable.png"/> Resource without specified resource
        link</para>
      <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/GreyDiamond.png"/>
        <inlinegraphic fileref="images/2.png" contentdepth="10"/> CMDI node with subnodes; number of
        subnodes indicated in the brackets.</para>
      <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/dataempty.png"/> Node has optional fields but contains no
        data</para>
      <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/written_resources_icon.png"/> Written resource </para>
      <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/video_resources_icon.png"/> Video resource </para>
      <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/audio_resources_icon.png"/> Audio resource </para>
      <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/image_resources_icon.png"/>Image resource </para>
      <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/lock.png" contentdepth="100%"/> Resource is locked and
        can only be opened by users with access rights.</para>
      <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/unlock.png" contentdepth="100%"/> Resource is unlocked
        for the user</para>
      <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/i.png"/>Info file</para>
      <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/unknown_type_archivable.png"/> In resources: archivable
        file of an unknown type</para>
      <para><inlinegraphic contentdepth="100%" fileref="images/file.png"/> File that is not an
        archivable format and therefore cannot be added as a resource </para>
      <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/favourites_icon.png"/> The node has been added to the
        list of the favourites and can be duplicated via the favourites add menu </para>
      <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/loading01.png"/> Node is currently being loaded </para>
      <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/not_found_icon.png"/> File not found</para>
      <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/vocabulary_closed.png" align="left" contentdepth="80%"/>
        Cosed controlled vocabulary</para>
      <para><inlinegraphic fileref="images/language1.png" align="left" contentdepth="100%"/>
        Language selection on field (e.g. Description language)</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>Starting Arbil</title>
    <para>When you open Arbil for the first time the <emphasis role="italic">wizard</emphasis>
      appears and gives you the ability to configure Arbil to your needs. The first window (Figure
      2.1) is a welcome window, press <emphasis role="italic">Next</emphasis> to move to the second
      step of the wizard. In this window (Figure 2.2) you select the metadata format i.e. IMDI or
      CMDI; you can choose one of them or both. In this manual we will assume you will select just
      CMDI. The third window (Figure 2.3) gives you the ability to choose the corpora and/or the
      profiles that will appear in the <emphasis role="bold">Remote corpus</emphasis> box. If you
      know the URL<footnote id="fn_url">
        <para>You can copy the URL of a corpus by selecting the node in the remote tree in Arbil
          when the wizard is not showing, right click and select 'Copy'; or get it from the IMDI
          browser by navigating to the corpus, right click the node and select 'Create bookmark' and
          copy the URL link. Then you can paste it into the box in the wizard.</para>
      </footnote> of the remote metadata that you will be working on frequently, you can add it to
      this list so that it will be available on the root level of the tree in the Remote corpus box.
      After finishing with <emphasis role="bold">Remote locations</emphasis> press <emphasis
        role="bold">Next</emphasis> (Figure 2.4) and then <emphasis role="bold">Finish</emphasis>.
      You can reopen the wizard by choosing <emphasis role="bold">Run setup wizard</emphasis> in the
        <emphasis role="bold">Help</emphasis> menu.</para>
    <para>
      <figure>
        <title>Welcome to Arbil </title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/welcome.png" contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1" width="60%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <figure>
        <title>Choosing CMDI</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/CMDI start.png" width="50%" contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1"
            />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <figure>
        <title>Select CMDI profile</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/cmdi_Select_Cmdi_profile.png" contentdepth="100%"
              scalefit="1" width="60%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </para>
    <para>
      <figure>
        <title>Remote locations</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/cmdi_Arbil_Wizard.png" scalefit="1" width="60%"
              contentdepth="100%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </para>
    <para>Arbil can be started in two ways, either via the webstart or by downloading the installer
      (see <ulink url="http://tla.mpi.nl/tools/tla-tools/arbil">here</ulink>). Note that the
      webstart does not work for Ubuntu; in this case you will have to download the installer
      version. </para>
    <section>
      <title>Language selection</title>
      <para>Arbil 2.5 allows you to change the language in which the application will open and work.
        At the moment, you can choose among: English (either the United Kingdom or the United States
        variants), German, Italian and Spanish. </para>
      <para>When you start the application for the first time, a dialog window will come out asking
        you to choose a language. After having chosen and selected OK, Arbil wizard will open in the
        language you have selected (see figures below). </para>
      <para>However, you can always change the language via the option <emphasis role="bold">Select
          language</emphasis> in the Help menu, which will open the same dialog window as before. </para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <title>Language selection</title>
          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo/>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/language_selection_italian.png" contentdepth="100%"
                  scalefit="1" width="50%"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <figure>
        <title>Arbil wizard</title>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo/>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/language_selection_wizard.png" contentdepth="100%" os=""
                scalefit="1" width="60%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="Ch_Basics">
    <title>Set-up</title>
    <para>
      <note>
        <para>Remember that if, once you have set up your Arbil page, you realize that the font size
          is either too small or too big, you can resize it as you like it via the options included
          in the <emphasis role="bold">View</emphasis> menu, i.e.: <emphasis role="bold">Larger
            font</emphasis>; <emphasis role="bold">Smaller font</emphasis>; <emphasis role="bold"
            >Reset font size</emphasis>.</para>
      </note>
    </para>
    <section id="Sec_Remote_Corpus">
      <title>Remote Corpus</title>
      <para>The Remote Corpus contains all the remote metadata. Currently it is not possible to add
        anything to remote corpora or edit it in general using Arbil. It is primarily used to view
        data and also allows you to import metadata into the Local corpus (discussed in <link
          linkend="Sec_Import_to_Local_Corpus">Section 3.2</link>) where they can then be
        modified.</para>
      <para>It has a tree-like structure in which each node contains multiple sub-branches. To open
        any of them, click on the bullet to the left of the node representing the branch or double
        click the node itself. This can be repeated for the sub-branches as well. In this way you
        can view the whole structure of the corpus. If you click the bullet again, the node will
        fold back.</para>
      <section>
        <title>Tree structure view</title>
        <para>As far as CMDI documents are concerned, it is possible to switch to a verbatim
          representation of the latter in the tree. This means that the structure of CMDI documents
          will be shown exactly as it is, with no kind of visual simplification. In order to have
          such a representation, select <emphasis role="bold">Show verbatim XML structure in tree
            for CMDI</emphasis> from the <emphasis role="bold">Options</emphasis> menu.</para>
      </section>
      <section id="Sec_Adding_Removing_Remote_Locations">
        <title>Adding and removing Remote Locations</title>
        <para>If you want to use remote CMDI metadata that are not available under remote corpus, or
          want to link them at root level, you can add them yourself, provided that you know the URL
          address of this remote metadata. Right click on the Remote Corpus top node and choose
            <emphasis role="bold">Add Remote Location</emphasis>. In the pop-up window enter the URL
          and press OK. The corpus should now appear in the main list of the Remote Corpus
          window.</para>
        <figure>
          <title>Adding a remote location</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata contentdepth="100%" fileref="images/Adding_a_remote_location.png"
                scalefit="1" width="60%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>Since you might not want to use all of the collections of CMDI instances in the Remote
          Corpus, it is also possible to remove any of the locations of the Remote Corpus at the
          root level so as to only display the collections that you need. This can be done at the
          root level only (see figure 3.1) by right clicking on the node (e.g. for MPI corpora) and
          selecting <emphasis role="bold">Remove Remote Location</emphasis>. If you have removed the
          default location, it is always possible to re-add them to the Remote Corpus by right
          clicking on it and selecting <emphasis role="bold">Add Default Remote
          Locations</emphasis>.</para>
        <para>To add a subnode to the root level, browse to the desired sub collection, right click
          on it and choose <emphasis role="bold">Copy</emphasis>. Then go back to the top node of
          the Remote Corpus and paste the URL in the dialogue box. The sub collection will now
          appear in the Remote Corpus tree. </para>
        <para>The corpus data on the Remote Corpus may sometimes be updated by the researchers. To
          be sure that you are working with the newest version of the available corpus, you can
          update it manually on the nodes that you believe have been altered. To do this, right
          click on the specific collection you want to update and select <emphasis role="bold"
            >Reload</emphasis>. </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Add to tree root</title>
        <para>It may happen that the branch you want to work on is located at a very low
          hierarchical position in your remote corpus. To avoid clicking on every single node in
          order to get to the one you need, you can select this one, right click on it, and select
          the option <emphasis role="bold">Add to Tree Root</emphasis>. A copy of it will be created
          and placed at the top of the Remote Corpus tree, so that you will not have to look for it
          anymore (see Bilingual Liceras Corpus example in the figure below).</para>
        <para>
          <figure>
            <title>Add to tree root</title>
            <screenshot>
              <screeninfo/>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/add_tree_root_CMDI.png" contentdepth="100%"
                    scalefit="1" width="60%"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>
          </figure>
        </para>
      </section>
      <section id="Sec_Viewing_Corpus_Information">
        <title>Viewing Remote Corpus Information</title>
        <para>In general, the easiest way to view the information of a node is to drag and drop it
          from the remote corpus into the grey working area on the bottom right. It is also possible
          to right click on the selected node and choose <emphasis role="bold">View
            Selected</emphasis>. In either case, a window pops up with the desired information
          listed in tables. This also enables you to view multiple nodes at the same time. </para>
        <para>To view <emphasis role="italic">multiple</emphasis> nodes, simply hold the Ctrl key on
          the keyboard while clicking on the desired nodes. Then drag them to the working area (or
          right click and select <emphasis role="bold">View selected</emphasis>). The figure below
          shows it.</para>
        <para>
          <note>
            <para>If you have an existing open table, it is also possible to add additional tree
              nodes of any form (i.e. collections and files). Simply drag any unselected node from
              the tree structure and drop it on the table. It will be automatically added to the
              table as a row.</para>
          </note>
        </para>
        <para>
          <figure>
            <title>Viewing multiple selected corpora</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata contentdepth="100%"
                  fileref="images/cmdi_Viewing_multiple_selected_corpora.png" scalefit="1"
                  width="100%"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </para>
        <para>There are also two other quick ways for viewing corpus information:</para>
        <para>(1) either you let your cursor rest above a collection or a node without clicking.
          Information about the collection will be displayed in the tool tip under the
          cursor;</para>
        <para>(2) or you click on a corpus node. Information, if available, will be displayed in the
          top right frame. </para>
        <para>When viewing information on multiple nodes, each row corresponds to one node while
          each column corresponds to one metadata field. By clicking on any of the column names, you
          can easily sort rows alphabetically within a given table.</para>
        <para>In a table that includes several different types of nodes notice that not all the
          elements are described in terms of the same field; for example, there are data categories
          that belong to one collection but not to another. Such data fields are marked in grey and
          are not available; the same applies to the Local Corpus (<link linkend="Sec_Local_Corpus"
            >see Section 3.2</link>).</para>
        <figure>
          <title>Not editable cells in a table</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata contentdepth="70%" fileref="images/cmdi_not_editable_cells_in_a_table.png"
                scalefit="1" width="80%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>In some cases you will see that, instead of a value, in a cell in the table there is a
          caption: &lt;multiple values>. This means that there is more than one value for this data
          category for this particular node. To see these values click on &lt;multiple values> and a
          new window will pop up with the information shown. </para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section id="Sec_Local_Corpus">
      <title id="Sec_local_corpus" os="">Local Corpus</title>
      <para>The Local Corpus <inlinegraphic fileref="images/top_node_local_corpus_icon.png"
          contentdepth="70%"/> is located beneath the Remote Corpus panel. Remember that the Local
        Corpus is the main working area and that changes made in the Local Corpus will not affect
        the remote matadata. The Local Corpus serves two main functions: 1) editing existing
        collection, 2) creating new collection. Section 3.2.1 explains how Local Corpora can be
        modified by (re)editing the data from the Remote Corpus. Section 3.2.2 explains how to
        create and subsequently modify new collections.</para>
      <section id="Sec_Import_to_Local_Corpus">
        <title id="sec_import_local_corpus">Import to Local Corpus</title>
        <para>If you have decided to work on a corpus from the archive you first need to import it
          from the Remote Corpus to your Local Corpus, and then you can edit it. To do so, select
          the node/session from the Remote Corpus and simply drag the item and drop it into the
          local corpus icon <inlinegraphic fileref="images/top_node_local_corpus_icon.png"
            scalefit="1" contentdepth="70%"/>. You can also right click on the corpus node you want
          to import and choose <emphasis role="bold">Import to Local Corpus</emphasis>. </para>
        <para>In the dialogue box that pops up you may want to check the option <emphasis
            role="bold">Import Resource Files (if available)</emphasis>, through which, as the name
          itself says, both the node and the possible resources that such node contains will be
          imported into the Local Corpus. Please be aware that: 1) Arbil cannot deal with resources
          that need authentication; 2) copying the resource files may take some time and will use
          disk space on your computer. </para>
        <para>Select <emphasis role="bold">Start</emphasis> to initiate the import process. Select
            <emphasis role="bold">Stop</emphasis> if you want to interrupt such process. </para>
        <figure>
          <title>Show details and options</title>
          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo/>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/import_lc_cmdi.png" contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1"
                  width="60%"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </figure>
        <para>Once the import process has started a message can appear, asking you whether you want
          to overwrite an existing local corpus/session node from the same original location. When
          is this option useful? Consider the likely scenario that you have imported a node from the
          Remote corpus and started editing it. If you want to reset the changes, you can reimport
          it from the Remote Corpus and answer "Yes" to the question "Overwrite?". You can apply
          this option to every branch of the corpora. </para>
        <para>You may want to check the option <emphasis role="bold">Remember my choice</emphasis>,
          so that the message will not come out again for the other already existing files that
          Arbil will encounter during the import process. </para>
        <para>
          <figure>
            <title>Overwrite message</title>
            <screenshot>
              <screeninfo/>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/overwrite_changes_cmdi.png" contentdepth="100%"
                    scalefit="1" width="60%"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>
          </figure>
        </para>
        <para>Once the import has finished you will see a window telling you how many Metadata Files
          have been processed. If you select <emphasis role="bold">Details</emphasis>, you will see
          all the possible errors that have occurred during the process. </para>
        <para>
          <figure>
            <title>Import completed</title>
            <screenshot>
              <screeninfo/>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/import_completed_CMDI.png" contentdepth="100%"
                    scalefit="1" width="60%"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>
          </figure>
        </para>
      </section>
      <section id="Sec_New_Corpora">
        <title>Creating profile instances</title>
        <para>Instead of copying an existing collection or corpus nodes from the Remote Corpus, you
          can also create your own metadata instances. Moreover, you can add an existing profile;
          with multiple profile instances it is possible to build a tree structure.</para>
        <para>To do so, select the top node of the Local Corpus (corpus node), right click it and
          select the option <emphasis role="bold">Add</emphasis> and then you can choose the profile
          or component(s) you want to add.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Creating (and describing) hierarchical collections</title>
        <para>In Arbil CMDI you can also create hierarchical collections of instances. The easiest
          way to do so is to create the parent and the child nodes <emphasis role="bold"
            >separately</emphasis> in the Local Corpus, as if they were two different examples of
          instances. Once both are there in the Local Corpus tree, simply drag the child node into
          the parent node. A message will appear asking you whether you want to move the node X to
          the node Y. After selecting <emphasis role="bold">Move</emphasis> you will see the Local
          Corpus tree structure changed (see figures below).</para>
        <para>
          <figure>
            <title>Creating parent and child node</title>
            <screenshot>
              <screeninfo/>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/create_parent_child_nodes.png" contentdepth="100%"
                    scalefit="1" width="60%"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>
          </figure>
          <figure>
            <title>Creating a hierarchy</title>
            <screenshot>
              <screeninfo/>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/create_hierarchy.png" contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1"
                    width="60%"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>
          </figure>
        </para>
        <para>
          <note>
            <para>The recommended Clarin profile to use in order to describe collections of
              instances is  <ulink
                url="http://catalog.clarin.eu/ds/ComponentRegistry?item=clarin.eu:cr1:p_1284723009187"
                >clarin.eu:cr1:p_1284723009187</ulink>.</para>
          </note>
        </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Local Corpus Storage Directory</title>
        <para>When Arbil is started for the first time a .arbil directory should be automatically
          created on your local machine. In it, and more specifically into a subfolder named
          ArbilWorkingFiles, the content of your Local Corpus should be located and saved. However,
          the location of your Local Corpus can always be changed. To do so, go to <emphasis
            role="bold">Options</emphasis> > <emphasis role="bold">Local Corpus Storage
            Directory</emphasis> > <emphasis role="bold">Move Local Corpus Storage
            Directory...</emphasis>. </para>
        <para>
          <note>
            <para>It may happen that Arbil detects multiple storage directories on your machine
              (which may be due to an older version of the application conflicting with a new one).
              In those cases you will be notified through a warning message, asking you what you are
              going to do with such storage directories. </para>
          </note>
        </para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section id="Sec_Working_Directories">
      <title>Working Directories</title>
      <para>Beneath the Local Corpus window, you will find two different tabs: <emphasis role="bold"
          >Files</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">Favourites</emphasis>. This section describes
        the Files tab and the functioning of its <emphasis role="bold">Working
          Directories</emphasis>, while <link linkend="Sec_Favourites">Section 3.4</link> below
        focuses on the Favourites tab. </para>
      <para>The Files tab is responsible for linking a folder from your computer to Arbil so that
        media files can be transferred into your corpus. It is advisable to have one or more folders
        on your computer that contains all the necessary files that you would like to upload to your
        corpus. This way, you can simply link this folder and retrieve all the necessary
        files.</para>
      <para>The option Files is selected by default. Its Working Directories are meant to keep at
        hand the resources that you want to add to your corpus (such as annotations, audio files,
        pictures etc.). To add a new Working Directory, right click on the Working Directory node
        and select <emphasis role="bold">Add Working Directory</emphasis>. Now browse to the
        directory you want to add, select it and click again on <emphasis role="bold">Add Working
          Directory</emphasis>. In the figure <link linkend="image_linked_folder">3.8</link>, the
        directory "Recursion pics" is about to be added to the Working directories, after which you
        will be able to access the media files present in this folder.</para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <title>Add working directories</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/WD1.png" contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1" width="70%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>After linking a directory to Arbil, you will have access to the folder. To import the
        media files (e.g. Droste.jpg) to a session of a corpus, simply drag and drop them into the
        desired session. </para>
      <para> </para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <title>Linked folder</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/WD2.png" contentdepth="100%" width="50%"
                id="image_linked_folder" scalefit="1"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>
        <note>
          <para>If you right click on Working Directories, you will also see that it is possible for
            Arbil to show you all hidden files (option <emphasis role="bold">Show hidden
              files</emphasis>). This option is useful when you want to include collection files
            which are normally hidden in your file manager.</para>
        </note>
      </para>
      <para>Browsing through the Working Directories is very similar to browsing through the Remote
        or the Local Corpus. To open/close a folder click on the bullet on the left of its name or
        double click on the name itself. If you have added or modified the content of a directory
        outside Arbil, you can update such content by right clicking Working Directories and
        selecting <emphasis role="bold">Reload</emphasis>.</para>
      <para>If you want to view the file information you can follow the instructions described in
        Section 3.2.2. (<link linkend="Sec_Viewing_Corpus_Information">Viewing Remote Corpus
          Information</link>). Remember that if you place the cursor over a file, an information
        window will appear that will give you a file description, including the information about
        whether the file is archivable or not. Archivable files can be uploaded to the server. Image
        3.7 shows an example of an archivable file:</para>
      <figure>
        <title>Archivable file</title>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo/>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata contentdepth="100%" fileref="images/archivable.png" scalefit="1"
                width="50%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>
      <para>Editable files from the Working Directory can also be opened by external applications.
        Right click a given file (e.g.. audio file, picture) and select <emphasis role="bold">Open
          in External Application</emphasis>.</para>
      <para>If the file is not archivable, the <inlinegraphic contentdepth="100%"
          fileref="images/file.png" width="2%"/> icon will appear. If you hold the mouse pointer on
        the file, you will see the following information:</para>
      <figure>
        <title>Unarchivable file</title>
        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo/>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata contentdepth="100%" fileref="images/unarchiveable.png" scalefit="1"
                width="100%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>
      <para>For the list of accepted file types and formats, check the <ulink
          url="http://www.mpi.nl/corpus/html/lamus/apa.html">LAMUS manual</ulink>. </para>
      <para>A file that is not supported by Arbil can be kept in Arbil anyway and still be added to
        a Session in the Local Corpus, thus overriding the decision of the internal type checker. To
        do so, right click on the unarchivable file and select <emphasis role="bold">Override Type
          Checker Decision</emphasis>; a pop up window will appear asking you to say whether the
        file is a <emphasis role="bold">MediaFile</emphasis> or a <emphasis role="bold"
          >WrittenResource</emphasis>; the <inlinegraphic contentdepth="100%"
          fileref="images/file.png" width="2%"/> will then change into an icon of either a media
        file or a written resource file, and you will be able to add it as a resource file into the
        Local Corpus. To open the file right click it again and select <emphasis role="bold">Open in
          External Application</emphasis>. Beware that overriding the type checker decision can
        cause your corpus not to be accepted into the archive (rejected by Lamus).</para>
      <para>In addition, if you have modified your uploaded file externally, you may want to check
        whether it is still accepted by Arbil. To do so, right click the file in Working Directories
        and select <emphasis role="bold">Force Type Checking</emphasis>. If something has happened
        to your file you will see its icon change.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="Sec_Favourites">
      <title>Favourites</title>
      <para>The tab <emphasis role="bold">Favourites</emphasis> is meant for storing elements that
        you would like to re-use in new node, such as <emphasis role="italic">actors, language
          elements, locations</emphasis>, etc. Node elements that can be saved in Favourites are
        CMDI instances, or any subnodes. When taken to the favorites tab, such elements are placed
        in their corresponding subcategories; i.e. if you drag an author, this will be automatically
        located under the category "Author". If you have a number of elements in your Favourite List
        and you are not certain what the content of a given element is, you can always place the
        cursor over it and wait for the tool tip (information window) to appear.</para>
      <figure>
        <title>Favourites List</title>
        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata contentdepth="100%" fileref="images/favorites_grouped_type_CMDI.png"
                scalefit="1" width="50%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>
      <para>In order to add an element from the local corpus to the Favourites List, right click its
        node and choose <emphasis role="bold">Add to Favourites List</emphasis>. The element now
        appears in the Favourites List. You can also just drag them from the corpus tree structure,
        right down to the Favourites List. If this element is needed again, you can place it into a
        preferable location in your Local Corpus either by dragging it from the Favourites list or
        by copying and pasting it in one of the Local Corpus (sub)branches. </para>
      <figure>
        <title>Adding to favourites via menu</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/cmdi_adding_to_favourites_via_menu.png" contentdepth="100%"
              scalefit="1" width="50%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para> </para>
      <para>Once you have completed your Favourites list, you can start using it. Let's say you want
        to add a particular Author to a session in your Local Corpus: in order to do so choose the
        session in question, right click it, select <emphasis role="bold">Add from
          Favourites</emphasis> and click on the desired author. Otherwise, you can simply drag and
        drop the author from the Favorites tab to session in the Local Corpus.<figure>
          <title>Adding from Favourites to a component</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/cmdi_Adding_from_favourites_to_a_component.png"
                contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1" width="60%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure></para>
      <para>Note that the items in the Favourite List can be viewed and edited in the same way as
        the elements of the Local Corpus (i.e. via the options of the right click context menu).
        This means that if you make changes to your favourites you will have to right click on them
        and select <emphasis role="bold">Save Changes to Disk</emphasis> to make them permanent (or
        use Ctrl/cmd+S). The favourites which have been edited turn blue, which indicates that they
        contain pending changes to be saved locally.</para>
      <para>Favorites can also be exported and/or (re)imported. In order to <emphasis role="bold"
          >export</emphasis> your favorites: right click on <emphasis role="bold"
          >Favorites</emphasis> (in the Favorites tab) and select <emphasis role="bold"
          >Import/Export Favorites</emphasis>. A window like the one in the figure below will
        appear. Select the favorites you want to export, then <emphasis role="bold">Export
          selection</emphasis>, and after having chosen the location where to export select
          <emphasis role="bold">Save</emphasis>. As soon as the export process is complete you will
        see a message confirming it and the folder containing the exported files will open.</para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <title>Export/Import Favourites</title>
          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo/>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/import_export_favourites_CMDI.png" contentdepth="100%"
                  scalefit="1" width="60%"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>As you can see from the image above, if you want to <emphasis role="bold"
          >import</emphasis> some favorites into Arbil you have to follow the same instructions as
        the ones explained for the export: right clich on favorites > select Import/Export
        Favorites. This time, though, choose <emphasis role="bold">Import from dick</emphasis>.
        Choose the (.config) file that you want to import and select <emphasis role="bold"
          >Open</emphasis>. You will see a message confirming the successful import, while in the
        Favorites tab you will see the just imported files.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title id="link_to_appendix">Managing Selected Profiles </title>
      <para>From the <emphasis role="bold">Options</emphasis> menu, choose <emphasis role="bold"
          >Templates and Profiles</emphasis>. A list of the available CMDI profiles will appear. You
        can select the profiles you need from the list or you can add new ones.<figure>
          <title>Available Profiles</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/cmdi_available_templets_and_profiles.png"
                contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1" width="60%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure></para>
      <para>The button <emphasis role="bold">Download all</emphasis> (see number 3 in the above
        picture) allows you to download all the available profiles, so that you will be able to see
        them also without an internet connection. </para>
      <para>
        <note>
          <para>Another way of having the profiles available also offline is to <emphasis
              role="italic">select them from the list when online</emphasis>, since they get
            downloaded as soon as they are selected. </para>
        </note>
      </para>
      <para>When you add new profiles manually, or there are changes on them, you need to reload the
        list through the button <emphasis role="bold">Reload Selection</emphasis> (number 2 figure
        above) in order for the changes to be visible. Note that you have to <emphasis role="italic"
          >quit and restart</emphasis> Arbil to fully validate the reload process. </para>
      <para>With the button <emphasis role="bold">Refresh List</emphasis> (number 1 figure above)
        the list of profiles available in the Component Registry will check for updates, so that you
        will get the latest list of profiles form the server. In this case, unlike with the "Reload"
        commad, you do not have to quit and restart Arbil in order for the changes to be visible. </para>
      <para>In order to add a new profile, select the option <emphasis role="bold">Add
          URL</emphasis> (it is located above the list of profiles; see figure above) and paste into
        it the URL of the profile you want to import. You can find the URL, for instance, in the
          <emphasis role="bold">Clarin</emphasis> website, under the <emphasis role="bold">Component
          Registry</emphasis>. Note that only published profiles appear by their name; otherwise,
        they are displayed in the list by their ID (something that starts with clarin.eu).<figure>
          <title>Add URL</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/cmdi_Add_URL.png" contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1"
                width="50%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure></para>
      <para>In order to use a profile, this needs first to be selected through the check box. Then,
        if you right click on the Local Corpus node and go to the Add option, another menu will open
        with the names or IDs of the profiles that are selected in the list. Choose the one you
        need. This will be imported and it will appear in your Local Corpus.</para>
      <para>
        <note>
          <para>A profiles' components can be edited directly in the Component Registry of the
            Clarin website. If you do so, remember that you have to add the URL to the Arbil list of
            profiles again (the process is the same as the one explained above: Options menu >
            Templates &amp; Profiles > Add URL > Reload > quit and restart). Once the modified
            profile has been added, if you go to the Local Corpus, right click it, and select Add,
            you will see two profiles with the same name but with different details/structures (the
            old one has not been replaced).</para>
        </note>
      </para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="Ch_Editing_Corpus_Structure">
    <title>Editing the structure of an instance</title>
    <para>This chapter focuses on how to develop the structure of the Local Corpus.</para>
    <sect1 id="Sec_Adding_new_Node">
      <title>Adding components and/or elements</title>
      <para>Once you have created/imported a collection, you can add new components or elements to
        any corpus node of the Local Corpus. To do so, right click on a corpus node, scroll down to
        Add and choose the components or elements that belong to the imported profile(s). Notice
        that in the figure below the profile "Comic book" has been selected. The components and
        elements which are displayed belong to that specific profile. Different ones will appear
        accordingly for each profile you decide to use.</para>
      <para>Notice how some menu items have the <inlinegraphic
          fileref="images/imdi_contains_data.png" contentdepth="60%"/> icon, whereas others have a
          <inlinegraphic fileref="images/new_field.png" contentdepth="60%"/> icon. The
          <inlinegraphic fileref="images/imdi_contains_data.png" contentdepth="60%"/> icon
        represents a component that will be displayed in the hierarchy whereas the <inlinegraphic
          fileref="images/new_field.png" contentwidth="" contentdepth="60%"/> icon adds a new field
        (discussed below).<figure>
          <title>Adding a new component or element</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/cmdi_Add_a_new_component.png" contentdepth="100%"
                scalefit="1" width="60%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure></para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="Sec_Adding_More_Descriptions">
      <title>Adding more field elements</title>
      <para>Generally, every profile contains a particular set of fields which can be edited. Adding
          <inlinegraphic fileref="images/new_field.png" contentdepth="50%"/> elements implies adding
        a new metadata field to the selected node.</para>
      <para><figure>
          <title>Standard field name</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/cmdi_Standard_field_name.png" contentdepth="100%"
                scalefit="1" width="70%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>Using the example of our ComicBook profile, it consists of field names which
        include one field per title. You might want to add an additional 'Title' field. To do so,
        right click on a node, Add > (e.g.) ComicBook Title. Some fields can be added multiple
        times, others can be added only once.</para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <title>Add new metadata field</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/cmdi_Add_new_metadata_field.png" contentdepth="100%"
                scalefit="1" width="60%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="Sec_Adding_Resource_Files">
      <title>Adding resource files to a metadata document</title>
      <para>The easiest way to add resource files (e.g. audio, video etc.) to a metadata document is
        to drag and drop a given element from the Working Directories to any existing node in a
        metadata document. There it will appear as a child node of the selected node.</para>
      <para>Note that not all file types are archivable. If a file is not archivable, you will not
        be able to drag and drop it (any problem with the file will be illustrated by the
          <inlinegraphic contentdepth="60%" fileref="images/file.png"/> icon).</para>
      <figure>
        <title>Adding a resource by dragging and dropping</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/cmdi_Adding a resource by dragging and dropping.png"
              contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1" width="70%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>It is also possible to manually add resources from a remote location, i.e. the archive
        or the web. This can be done by right clicking on a node, selecting <emphasis role="bold"
          >Insert Manual Resource Location</emphasis>, and adding the URL in the window that appears
        in the table area.</para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <title>Insert manual remote resources</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/cmdi_insert_manual_remote_resource.png" contentdepth="100%"
                scalefit="1" width="50%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>When adding multiple resources from the Working Directories to a CMDI file, they will
        get processed together and appear in a single table in the table area.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="Sec_Moving_Sessions">
      <title>Moving instances</title>
      <para>Arbil allows to move metadata from one location to another. To do so, select in your
        Local Corpus an instance or a collection you would like to move and drag and drop it to the
        new location. It is also possible to move subnodes of collection, e.g. Actors, across
        sessions. However not all locations will be accepted, depending on the type of the dragged
        node.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="Sec_Deleting_Corpus_Elements">
      <title>Deleting linked instances </title>
      <para>In order to delete metadata instances or child nodes, right click on a chosen element
        and select <emphasis role="bold">Delete</emphasis>. If you want to remove several elements
        at a time, choose them all while holding the Ctrl (or Shift) button. Right click on the
        selected elements and chose Delete. In each case you will have to confirm the
        deletion.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Saving changes</title>
      <para>The changes to your files are not applied automatically. You have to save them yourself.
        To save the changes made in your local corpus: 1) right click on the node and choose
          <emphasis role="bold">Save Changes to Disk</emphasis>; 2) from <emphasis role="bold"
          >File</emphasis> menu select <emphasis role="bold">Save Changes</emphasis>; 3) use the key
        short cut (i.e. Ctrl+S/cmd+S).</para>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="Ch_Editing_Metadata">
    <title>Editing the metadata</title>
    <sect1 id="Sec_One_Cell_Editing">
      <title>Editing one cell</title>
      <para>To edit a metadata document or a collection just click on it (A), or select it and
        choose <emphasis role="bold">View Selected</emphasis> (B). In the window that appears, click
        on the field you want to change. Type in the new value: typing in an existing cell will
        start editing for replacing the existing content. Pressing the F2-key on windows/linux or
        CTRL-U-key on a Mac will start editing without removing content. Press <emphasis role="bold"
          >Enter</emphasis> to go to the next value. If the value you have typed is too long for the
        cell, the <emphasis role="bold">Long Field Editor</emphasis> will open automatically in
        order to edit this value. (<link linkend="sec_Long_field_editor">section 5.2</link>)</para>
      <figure>
        <title>Editing</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/cmdi_simple_editing.png" contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1"
              width="70%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>Some of the cells have a closed vocabulary, <inlinegraphic
          fileref="images/vocabulary_closed.png" contentdepth="50%"/>, (figure 5.2). When you double
        click the field you need, a drop-down menu will appear showing you available default values
        from which you can choose the one that fits your data. In controlled vocabulary fields
        'type-ahead' functionality is available; to confirm a suggestion, press Enter or type a
        comma in multi-CV to add another value.</para>
      <figure>
        <title>Closed vocabularies</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/cmdi_closed_vocaboulary.png" contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1"
              width="60%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Attributes</title>
      <para>It is possible to fill in or modify fields which contain attributes by right clicking on
        a selected node and choosing View Selected. Once the node has been displayed, the attributes
        fields are ready to be edited. There is also the possibility of working on them through the
        Long Field Editor. In case of long descriptions, one or more attribute fields can be edited
        here. </para>
      <para>Note that whether attributes are present or not depends on the profile that has been
        selected.</para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <title>Attributes</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/cmdi_edit_attributes.png" contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1"
                width="70%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>In the tooltip which appears hovering on a field, you can also see information about the
        attributes of that particular field. The number of potential attributes, as well as the
        value for the attributes that have one specified are displayed too. For an overview of all
        the possible attributes, open the field in The Long Field Editor (<link
          linkend="sec_Long_field_editor">Section 5.3</link>).</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="sec_Long_field_editor">
      <title>Long field editor</title>
      <para>The Long Field Editor (LFE) allows the user to edit long values, such as descriptions.
        The LFE works either automatically or manually. If you want to add a long description in a
        cell you can right click on the field in the table and select <emphasis role="bold">Open in
          Long Field Editor</emphasis>. In the window that appears you can add new text and/or edit
        the already present text. If a field already contains a long value and you wish to edit it,
        double click on it; the LFE will open automatically. </para>
      <para>The LFE can be opened on a selected node by right clicking on it and selecting <emphasis
          role="bold">Edit in Long Field Editor</emphasis>. The LFE opens on the first field under
        the node (generally the field <emphasis role="bold">Name</emphasis>), you can then navigate
        in the fields by using the <emphasis role="italic">previous</emphasis> and <emphasis
          role="italic">next</emphasis> buttons (1). The field you are currently in appears on the
        top of the LFE (2). The text appears and can be edited in the white area (3).</para>
      <para>Changes made in the LFE get applied to the field as soon as the LFE is closed or by
        pressing the <emphasis role="italic">previous</emphasis> or <emphasis role="italic"
          >next</emphasis> buttons.</para>
      <figure>
        <title>Long Field Editor</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/long_field_editor.png" contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1"
              width="70%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Delete field(s)</title>
      <para>Fields can also be deleted both for the metadata table of a single instance (see figure
        below), and from the one containing several nodes. As far as <emphasis role="bold">one
          single instance</emphasis> is concerned, you have to open such instance in the table area
        (either via right click > <emphasis role="bold">View selected</emphasis>, or simply by
        dragging and dropping the instance in the main area). Then select the field you want to
        delete, right click it and select <emphasis role="bold">Delete 1 field(s) "..."</emphasis>.
        Note that mandatory fields are NOT deletable; in case of a mandatory field you will not be
        able to see the delete option.</para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <title>Delete field from single instance</title>
          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo/>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/delete_field_single_instance_CMDI.png"
                  contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1" width="70%"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>In case of multiple instances in one single table (see figure below), what changes is
        the layout of the table itself, but the deletion process is the same as the one explained
        above for single instances. Open the instances in the table area, choose the field you want
        to delete, right click on it and select <emphasis role="bold">Delete field from all
          nodes</emphasis>. Note that, as before, mandatory fields CANNOT be deleted. Unlike with
        single instances, though, here you will always be able to see the delete option, the only
        difference being that in case of undeletable field a message will pop out telling you that
        that specific field cannot be deleted from the nodes.</para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <title>Delete field from several instances</title>
          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo/>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/delete_field_several_instances_CMDI.png"
                  contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1" width="70%"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </figure>
      </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="Sec_Editing_Multiple_Cells">
      <title>Editing multiple cells</title>
      <para>It will often be the case that a piece of information (e.g.. continent, country, address
        etc.) has to be repeated across the metadata documents. Instead of typing this data in every
        document, you can copy-paste it at once into all the relevant fields. Choose the relevant
        metadata documents by holding Ctrl and clicking on them. Then right click one of the
        selected items and choose View Selected. You will see a window appearing in which you can
        edit the documents.</para>
      <para>To edit the selected metadata documents, take the following steps:</para>
      <para>1. Fill one of the fields / choose a default value from the drop-down menu that you need
        (e.g. Country). If one of these fields is already filled in with the relevant information,
        skip this step.</para>
      <para>2. Right click on one of the selected cell and select <emphasis role="bold"
          >Copy</emphasis>.</para>
      <para>3. Select the fields where you want to paste the copied information (one by one) by
        holding Ctrl and clicking on them. Right click on one of the selected fields and chose
          <emphasis role="bold">Paste</emphasis>.</para>
      <figure>
        <title>Pasting data into multiple cells</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/cmdi_pasting_data_into_multiple_cells.png"
              contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>If you want to copy a value into <emphasis role="bold">all</emphasis> the cells of a
        certain column, select the field you want to copy, right click it and chose <emphasis
          role="bold">Copy Cell to Whole Column</emphasis>. All the cells in the column will be
        changed accordingly. Note, however, that this option is only applicable to one column at a
        time.</para>
      <figure>
        <title>Copying the value of a cell to all the cells of a column</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata contentdepth="100%" fileref="images/cmdi_copy_to-the_whole_column.png"
              scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>It is also possible to copy-paste values to multiple columns simultaneously. To do so,
        while holding Ctrl (or cmd), select the relevant cells of a metadata file, right click one
        of them and choose <emphasis role="bold">Copy</emphasis>.</para>
      <figure>
        <title>Copying values from columns in one metadata file</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/cmdi_copy_values_from_columns.png" contentdepth="100%"
              scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>Now choose the cells within the selected columns into which you want to paste the copied
        value by Ctrl (or cmd) clicking on them (you can also draw a box over them with the cursor),
        right click one of the cells and select <emphasis role="bold">Paste</emphasis>. The values
        will be pasted into the appropriate columns.</para>
      <para>Note that you cannot copy-paste data from different rows, only from different
        columns.</para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <title>Pasting values from two columns into several metadata files</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/cmdi_pasting_values_two_columns.png" contentdepth="100%"
                width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>It is possible to show the entire document containing any specific node that is shown in
        the horizontal table view. To do so, right click a cell or row and select <emphasis
          role="bold">Show Context</emphasis>. This menu item opens the hierarchical 'sub-nodes'
        view on the root of the document that contains the selected cell or row.<figure>
          <title>Show Context Menu</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/show_context_CMDI.png" contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1"
                width="70%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure></para>
      <sect2>
        <title><emphasis role="italic">Find</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic"
            >Replace</emphasis></title>
        <para>Another option in editing cells is the <emphasis role="italic">Find and
            Replace</emphasis> option activated by pressing, when you are in a table, CTRL/CMD+F, or
          by right clicking on a cell and selecting the option <emphasis role="bold"
            >Find/Replace</emphasis>. In both cases a line appears at the bottom of the table with
          two boxes (figure below); the left box (marked in red) is used to define the term you
          intend to find; the right box (marked in green) is used to define the term to be replaced
          with. By pressing the <emphasis role="bold">Find Next</emphasis> key the term specified in
          the first box is highlighted in the table; now you can either replace such term by
          pressing the <emphasis role="bold">Replace Selected</emphasis> key, or skip it and move to
          the next by pressing Find Next. Once you have moved to the next term in the table, you
          cannot go to a previous term. In that case you will have to manually select a previous
          cell to start from and continue searching.</para>
        <para>
          <figure>
            <title>Find and Replace</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/find_and_replace.png" scalefit="1" contentdepth="100%"
                  width="70%"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Editing All Metadata of a Subnode </title>
      <para>It is also possible for the user of Arbil to get access to all metadata under a node in
        a hierarchical order (figure below), as the order of the (sub)sessions, so as to edit them.
        To do this, right click on a metadata document on the tree view and select <emphasis
          role="bold">Edit All Metadata</emphasis>. Editing can be done in all cells in the way it
        has already been described.</para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <title>Edit/view all metadata</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/cmdi_edit_all-metadata.png" contentdepth="100%"
                scalefit="1" width="70%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="Sec_Customizing_Column_Views">
      <title>Customizing Column Views</title>
      <para>When viewing/editing multiple elements in a table, sometimes there are many columns to
        go through. It is possible to reduce them by choosing which columns you want to see or which
        columns you want to hide. Right click the header of any column, i.e. Name, and select the
        option <emphasis role="bold">Edit this Column View</emphasis>. In the window that pops up,
        you can select the columns that you want to show <emphasis role="bold">Show Only</emphasis>
        or hide <emphasis role="bold">Hide</emphasis> (if you check only the Hide column, the
        unchecked field names will be shown in the table). It is important to know that the
        column(s) which are hidden through this particular window, are not removed from the corpus
        itself.</para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <title>Choosing columns</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/cmdi_choosing_columns.png" contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1"
                width="80%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>So let's say that you have <emphasis role="italic">Date</emphasis> and <emphasis
          role="italic">Description</emphasis> marked as <emphasis role="italic">Show
          only</emphasis> (see figure below). This means that if you would now use this window to
        check out a node that has other categories than the ones selected with the option <emphasis
          role="italic">Show only</emphasis>, then these categories will not be displayed. So the
        window in this particular example will only have two columns.</para>
      <para>If you have a table with: Name, Title and Description and you set the Description to
        Hide, it means that Description will never be shown. But if the elements that you add to the
        window have other categories, these will still be displayed and the number of columns will
        increase accordingly (assuming that you don't use the show only option).</para>
      <para>One more option of customizing the column view is the function <emphasis role="bold"
          >Limit View to Current Columns</emphasis>, which you will find by right clicking the
        header of a column. When chosen, this mode will freeze the current columns view, meaning
        that no matter what element you add to the window, only the current categories (columns)
        will be shown. </para>
      <para>It is also possible to set the width of the columns by dragging the right or left edge
        of the column. This applies to arbitrary open tables as well as saved column views.</para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <title>Editing column view</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/editing-column-view.png" scalefit="1" width="70%"
                contentdepth="100%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>It is also possible to hide a column from the current view. To do so, right click on the
        column that you do not want to be displayed and choose <emphasis role="bold">This column
          (...)</emphasis> > <emphasis role="bold">Hide Column</emphasis>. </para>
      <figure>
        <title>Hiding one column</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata contentdepth="100%" fileref="images/cmdi_hide_one_column.png" scalefit="1"
              width="100%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>
        <note>
          <para>The right click menu option <emphasis role="bold">This column (...)</emphasis> also
            serves to adjust the size of the columns. Through the secondary options (see figure
            above) you can either make the column size fix (<emphasis role="bold">Fixed column
              size</emphasis>) or to make the columns big enough in order for their content to fit
              (<emphasis role="bold">Make column fit contents</emphasis>). </para>
        </note>
      </para>
      <para>Once you have hidden the unnecessary columns, you can save this view by right clicking
        any of the headers of the columns and choosing <emphasis role="bold">Save Current Column
          View</emphasis>. Give the column view a name and select <emphasis role="bold"
          >OK</emphasis>. </para>
      <figure>
        <title>Saving Column View</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata contentdepth="100%" fileref="images/cmdi_saving_column_view.png" scalefit="1"
              width="60%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>Currently it is NOT possible to delete the column views that you create.</para>
      <para>The view you have just saved is also applicable to other tables. Right click the header
        column of the new Table, select <emphasis role="bold">Column View for this Table</emphasis>
        and choose the view you want. By default, there are two views already defined and cannot be
        modified: <emphasis role="bold">All</emphasis> (i.e. all columns are displayed), and
          <emphasis role="bold">Minimal</emphasis> (i.e. only <emphasis role="italic"
          >Name</emphasis>, <emphasis role="italic">Title</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic"
          >Description</emphasis> are displayed). It is important not to forget that each view you
        create initially is window specific. In this way you can use different views for different
        windows. </para>
      <para>It is also possible to set your modified column view as the default column view that
        will appear in all tables you open. To do so, go to <emphasis role="bold">Options</emphasis>
        menu in Arbil toolbar, select <emphasis role="bold">Column View For New Tables</emphasis>
        and the preferred column view. This is now your default column view. (see number 1 in the
        figure below).</para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <title>Setting new default column view</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/default_collumn view.png" contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1"
                width="60%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>
        <note>
          <para>Column views that have been modified and multiple open windows in the working area,
            either saved or unsaved, are available after closing Arbil once the programme starts
            again exactly in the same way they were before closing it provided the <emphasis
              role="bold">Save Windows on Exit</emphasis> is activated in the Options menu (see
            number 2 in the figure above).</para>
        </note>
      </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="Sec_Highlighting_Cells">
      <title>Highlighting cells with the same value</title>
      <para>If you want to see which cells in a table have the same value, right click the
        appropriate cell and choose <emphasis role="bold">Highlight Matching Cells</emphasis>. Cells
        with the same value will be highlighted. You can do this with more than one cell; each new
        group of matching cells will be given a different colour. To remove the highlight, right
        click on a cell and choose: <emphasis role="bold">Clear Cell Highlight</emphasis>.</para>
      <figure>
        <title>Highlighting cells</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata contentdepth="100%" fileref="images/cmdi_highlighting_cells.png" scalefit="1"
              width="70%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Track Table Selection in Tree</title>
      <para>It may be the case that you have, in the main area of the application (i.e. the bottom
        right part in the figure below) an open table with many elements displayed. Given this high
        amount of resources/sessions, you may not be able to recognize which one you need, or else
        which is which. From the Options menu mark the option <emphasis role="bold">Track Table
          Selection in Tree</emphasis>: now if you select an item in the table, its corresponding
        location on the tree will be highlighted, thus enabling you to know which and where you
        required item is. </para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <title>Track Table Selection inTree</title>
          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo/>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/track_table_selection_CMDI.png" contentdepth="100%"
                  scalefit="1" width="70%"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </figure>
      </para>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="Ch_Exploring">
    <title>Searching</title>
    <sect1 id="Sec_Searching">
      <title>Searching Local Corpus</title>
      <para>The search option allows you to find a value throughout either the Local Corpus or the
        Remote Corpus. To do so, right click on a given node you want to search and select <emphasis
          role="bold">Search</emphasis> (you might also choose a number of nodes by holding Ctrl and
        clicking on them). A window will appear in which you can specify where and what exactly you
        want to search e.g. within Corpus, Session, Catalogue, Actor etc.</para>
      <figure>
        <title>Selecting search locations</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata contentdepth="100%" fileref="images/cmdi_selecting_search_location.png"
              scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>In the search window you can further specify in which column you want to search. By
        clicking on <emphasis role="bold">&lt;column (optional)></emphasis> a drop down list
        appears, containing pre-defined common values and previously entered column names; it is
        also possible to manually add column names to this list, or to remove arbitrary items by
        selecting the value and pressing the <emphasis role="bold">delete</emphasis> key on your
        keyboard; deleted values have to be retyped and searched for in order to appear in the drop
        down list again. After specifying the column (e.g. Name), give the value name you look for,
        e.g. "Blance", and click on <emphasis role="bold">search</emphasis>.</para>
      <para>By selecting either <emphasis role="italic">Equal</emphasis> (<inlinegraphic
          fileref="images/Equal.jpeg" contentdepth="50%"/>) or <emphasis role="italic"
          >Unequal</emphasis> (<inlinegraphic fileref="images/Unequal.jpg" contentdepth="50%"/>),
        you will need to specify whether your search results should match the word you filled in or
        rather show you where this word does not appear.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Display of Search Results</title>
      <para>Suppose the search we are going to make is: Creator (&lt;column (optional)>) equals (==)
        Annick (&lt;value (optional)>). After clicking on search, the results will be displayed in a
        table such as the one below. In case the content of one or more cell exactly matches the
        value you have searched for, the cell(s) will be highlighted.</para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <title>Display of Search Results</title>
          <screenshot>
            <screeninfo/>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/display_search_results_CMDI.png" contentdepth="100%"
                  scalefit="1" width="70%"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </figure>
      </para>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>Exporting and Importing data</title>
    <sect1 id="Exporting_data_from_Arbil">
      <title>Exporting data from Arbil</title>
      <para>After creating new corpus branches or editing corpora from an already existing archive,
        you can save your files and upload them to the appropriate archive. In order to do so you
        need to export your files from Arbil. Select the modified nodes or the branch that contains
        the modified parts, right click on them and select <emphasis role="bold">Export</emphasis>.
        A dialogue box will pop up, in which you choose the location of the export and the name of
        the file. To complete the export, click on <emphasis role="bold">Export Branch Destination
          Directory</emphasis>.</para>
      <figure>
        <title>Exporting files</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata contentdepth="100%" fileref="images/cmdi_Exporting_files.png" scalefit="1"
              width="80%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>The following message may appear if the destination directory is not empty:</para>
      <figure>
        <title>Export alert message</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata contentdepth="100%" fileref="images/exporting_branch_details.png"
              scalefit="1" width="50%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>Selecting <emphasis role="bold">OK</emphasis> will lead you to a message window which is
        the same as the one seen above regarding the import into the Local Corpus (see <xref
          linkend="fig_exportBranch"/>).</para>
      <figure id="fig_exportBranch">
        <title>Export window with details</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/export_branch_cmdi.png" contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1"
              width="60%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <sect2>
        <title>More export options</title>
        <para>The export window offers advanced export options. These can be accessed by clicking
          the button <emphasis role="bold">More options</emphasis> (see <xref
            linkend="fig_exportBranch_optionsExpanded"/>). </para>
        <figure id="fig_exportBranch_optionsExpanded">
          <title>Export window - more options</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/exportBranch_optionsExpanded.png" contentdepth="100%"
                scalefit="1" width="60%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>The following options are available: <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Convert exported IMDI to CMDI</emphasis>: This option
                converts the exported IMDI files to the CMDI file type. This gives you the
                possibility to import the exported files to a CMDI archive.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Rename Metadata Files </emphasis>: Rename files to match
                local corpus tree names.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Limit Characters in File Names</emphasis>: This replaces
                all characters in the filenames which are not accepted by LAMUS. Currently accepted
                are digits, non-accented letters, dots (.), underscores (_) and hyphens (-). All
                other characters will be replaced.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Export process details</title>
        <para>By selecting <emphasis role="bold">Details</emphasis> you can inspect the export
          process details including possible erros (see <xref
            linkend="fig_exportBranch_everythingExpanded"/>).</para>
        <figure id="fig_exportBranch_everythingExpanded">
          <title>Export window - details</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/exportBranch_everythingExpanded.png" contentdepth="100%"
                scalefit="1" width="60%"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Importing data into Arbil</title>
      <para>In Arbil there is a number of possibilities to import the data. </para>
      <para>The first way to import data is from the Remote corpus to the Local corpus, either by
        right clicking on the required branch in the remote corpus and selecting <emphasis
          role="bold">Import to Local Corpus</emphasis>, or by dragging and dropping it. </para>
      <para>If you want to import data from you local computer disk, or from the network, go to
          <emphasis role="bold">File</emphasis> menu, select <emphasis role="bold"
        >Import</emphasis>, and then choose the required data from your local disk, or from the
        network; your data wil be imported at the root level. </para>
      <para>In addition, at Local Corpus level, the context menu that comes out when right clicking
        one of the nodes includes further import options:</para>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">Import Branch</emphasis> (i.e. importing a piece of your corpus)
        gives you the ability to import part of your corpus from your disk to the Local corpus. </para>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">Reimport this branch</emphasis> (i.e. re-importing form the remote
        corpus): in order to make changes to a corpus you have already exported to the Remote corpus
        via Lamus, it is essential to reimport such corpus to the Local corpus and choose Yes to the
        message question "Overwrite?".</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title id="Sec_using_an_external_editor">Using an External Editor</title>
      <para>As is has already been noticed, it is possible to open, view and modify the data using
        external editors such as spread sheets or text editors. Overall the process is done by
        moving data from Arbil to the external editor, making the necessary changes, and then moving
        them back to Arbil. </para>
      <para>However, possibilities of moving data back into Arbil are currently very <emphasis
          role="italic">limited</emphasis>. It is possible to do any of the following: <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Copy single field values (individual cells) from the external editor into
              Arbil;</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>In case of the IMDI Session root node, save your data in <emphasis role="italic"
                >CSV format</emphasis>, and then import them to Arbil by right clicking on the node
              where you want to copy them back and selecting <emphasis role="bold">Import
                CSV</emphasis>. This way you will be able to import the data in a table format; in
              any other case you will have to import the edited data column by column, but not all
              at once;</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>If cells in a table corresponding to a single metadata file are copied, then the
              data will be in a format that can then be pasted back into any table in Arbil,
              provided that the data maintains the same formatting.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>The following functions are currently <emphasis role="italic">not available</emphasis>: <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Pasting of multiple rows (i.e. data representing multiple nodes) into Arbil, even
              if the table in Arbil has an identical structure;</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Pasting of multiple values in general unless their structure corresponds to one of
              the options listed above;</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Importing CSV to any other type of node than the Session root.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>To open the data in an external editor (i.e. Ms Excel), select and copy the data from
        the table, then paste them in the editor you wish to use.</para>
      <figure>
        <title>Editing data in an External editor</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata contentdepth="100%" fileref="images/cmdi_editing_in_external_editor.png"
              scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>External application</title>
      <para>By selecting <emphasis role="italic">Open in External Application</emphasis> you can
        view and edit resources and metadata in the application that your computer chooses by
        default, such as a media player for a video file, or a text editor for a text file.</para>
      <figure>
        <title>Viewing data in external application</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/cmdi_viewing_in_external_application.png" contentdepth="100%"
              scalefit="1" width="60%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>Exiting Arbil</title>
    <para>Before exiting Arbil make sure that you have saved all your changes. This can easily be
      done by the key short-cut CTRL/CMD+S.</para>
    <para>You can exit Arbil by closing the main window, or through <emphasis role="italic"
        >File</emphasis> -> <emphasis role="italic">Exit</emphasis> on Windows or Linux, or Arbil ->
        <emphasis role="italic">Quit Arbil </emphasis>on Mac OS. In case of unsaved changes a
      message will appear and ask if you wish to <emphasis role="italic">Save Changes Before
        Exiting</emphasis>; choose <emphasis role="italic">Yes</emphasis> or <emphasis role="italic"
        >No</emphasis>, Arbil is now closed.</para>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>Shortcut Keys</title>
    <para>In Arbil you can use the following shortcuts:</para>
    <table>
      <title>General shortcut keys</title>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>CTRL/CMD+A</entry>
            <entry>Select all</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>CTRL/CMD+F</entry>
            <entry>Find &amp; Replace </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>CTRL/CMD+S</entry>
            <entry>Save</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>CTRL/CMD+W</entry>
            <entry>Close topmost window</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>CTRL/CMD+SHIFT+W</entry>
            <entry>Close all windows</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>CTRL+TAB</entry>
            <entry>Next window</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>CTRL/CMD+SHIFT+TAB</entry>
            <entry>Previous window</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>CTRL+P/CMD+P</entry>
            <entry>Hide/Show the selection preview</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>CTRL++/CMD++</entry>
            <entry>Increase the font size used in the application</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>CTRL+-/CMD+-</entry>
            <entry>Decrease the font size used in the application</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>CTRL+0/CMD+0</entry>
            <entry>Reset the font size used in the application to the default value</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>ENTER (in the tree)</entry>
            <entry>Open the current tree selection in a table</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>DELETE (in the tree)</entry>
            <entry>Delete the selected node from the tree</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <table>
      <title>Table short cut keys</title>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>CTRL/CMD+A</entry>
            <entry>Select all</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>CTRL/CMD+C</entry>
            <entry>Copy</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>CTRL/CMD+V</entry>
            <entry>Paste</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>CTRL/CMD+Z</entry>
            <entry>Undo</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>DELETE</entry>
            <entry>Delete the contents of the current table cell and start editing</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>ESC</entry>
            <entry>Cancel editing of the current cell</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>CTRL+ENTER</entry>
            <entry>Edit a cell in a new window</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <table>
      <title>Tree short cut keys</title>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>DELETE</entry>
            <entry>Delete the selected node in the tree</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <table>
      <title>Long field editor short cut keys</title>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>CTRL+UP</entry>
            <entry>Go to previous field</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>CTRL+DOWN</entry>
            <entry>Go the next field</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>CTRL+LEFT</entry>
            <entry>Go to previous tab</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>CTRL+RIGHT</entry>
            <entry>Go to next tab</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>Technical details</title>
    <section>
      <title>Custom File types Configuration</title>
      <para>It is possible to override the default set of file types that the type checker should
        recognize as archivable resources.</para>
      <para>To do so, place your custom filetypes.txt configuration file in the root of your local
        storage directory (to find out what that is, select Local Corpus Storage Directory from the
        Options menu). It will then automatically be installed in the type checker as soon as type
        checking takes place for the first time during a session. You will need to restart Arbil if
        it is already running.</para>
      <para>For information about obtaining or creating a custom file types configuration, please
        contact your administrator.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Templates</title>
      <para>Templates are currently in development, but they will be used to customise the
        components added via the "Add" menu.</para>
      <para>To create a new template, create a directory in the ".arbil/templates" directory. This
        is where all the files relevant to that template will be stored. This directory will now be
        selectable via the "options/templates" menu.</para>
      <para>Each template can have its own XSL which is used via the "view formatted" menu. The XSL
        must be in the selected templates directory and be called "format.xsl". For example:
        .arbil/templates/{template name}/format.xsl. If there are any additional files required by
        the XSL they can be placed in the same directory as the XSL file.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Plugins</title>
      <para>Plugins add extra functionality to Arbil. They are provided as '.jar' files that can be
        placed in a special location where Arbil will detect them and add them as items to the
        'Plugins' menu (which is hidden unless plugins have actually been detected).</para>
      <para>To install a plugin, place the .jar file in one of the following directories: </para>
      <para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>~/ArchivingPlugins (Linux or MacOS)</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>%APPDATA%/ArchivingPlugins (Windows)</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>%USERPROFILE%/ArchivingPlugins (Windows)</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>&lt;ARBIL STORAGE DIRECTORY>/ArchivingPlugins</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>If none of the locations already exist, you can create one. Some options will not be
        available on all operating systems. ~ denotes the user's home directory on Unix systems.
        %APPDATA% and %USERPROFILE% are system environments available in Windows. Use the 'run
        command' option (Windows key + R) to open locations that contain the environment
        variable.</para>
      <para>&lt;ARBIL STORAGE DIRECTORY> is the directory called .arbil that contains the
        configuration files and by default is the parent directory of the working files
        directory.</para>
      <para>After installing the plugin you should restart Arbil for it to become available in the
        Plugins menu of the menu bar.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Custom logging configuration</title>
      <para>If present, a logging configuration will be read and applied from a file called
        'logging.properties' in the application configuration directory ('.arbil'). An example of
        such a configuration is given below.</para>
      <para>The logging output (visible in the log console of the Help menu) can be observed from
        different levels of detail. Such levels are: <emphasis role="bold">ALL</emphasis>, <emphasis
          role="bold">FINE</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">INFO</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold"
          >WARNING</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">SEVERE</emphasis>. Note that the log console is
        visible only when the application is installed, i.e. NOT with the webstart version. </para>
      <para><screen format="linespecific" width="100%">
        handlers= java.util.logging.FileHandler, java.util.logging.ConsoleHandler
        
        # Default global logging level.
        .level = ALL
        
        ############################################################
        # Handler specific properties.
        # Describes specific configuration info for Handlers.
        ############################################################
        
        # default file output is in user's home directory.
        java.util.logging.FileHandler.pattern = %h/arbil.log
        java.util.logging.FileHandler.level = WARNING
        java.util.logging.FileHandler.formatter = java.util.logging.SimpleFormatter
        
        # Limit the message that are printed on the console to INFO and above.
        java.util.logging.ConsoleHandler.level = FINE
        java.util.logging.ConsoleHandler.formatter = java.util.logging.SimpleFormatter
        
        
        ############################################################
        # Facility specific properties.
        ############################################################
        
        java.level = WARNING
        javax.level = WARNING
        sun.level = WARNING
        
        nl.mpi.arbil.level = FINEST
        nl.mpi.flap.level = FINEST
        nl.mpi.level = FINEST
      </screen></para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <appendix>
    <title>CMDI ecosystem</title>
    <para>CMDI - “Component Metadata infrastructure” – is a metadata framework in which metadata
      blueprints can be described and reused. </para>
    <para>Metadata is data about data, giving various kinds of information about the data contained,
      e.g. about protagonists, places, the date of gathering data etc. To manage this metadata in a
      diligent way certain ready-made options for description can be used which facilitate the
      production of well-ordered information. </para>
    <para>In addition, to create metadata (components) from scratch, CMDI allows you to use existing
      description options –blueprints in the form of ‘profiles and components’ (see <xref
        linkend="figure_1"/> below). These existing blueprints can be edited in the component
      registry according to individual needs, if necessary. </para>
    <para>Furthermore, Arbil also allows editing the content of metadata descriptions. </para>
    <para>
      <figure>
        <title id="figure_1"> Building profiles from components according to the projects’
          individual demands with CMDI in the component browser. </title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/Appendix_Component_CMDImanualdummies_image0.png" scalefit="1"
              contentdepth="100%" width="100%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </para>
    <para>CLARIN has established this infrastructure of ready-made building blocks (components) to
      overcome “dispersion of metadata in diverse formats” (see <ulink
        url="http://www.clarin.eu/node/3219">CLARIN website</ulink> for more information about
      CMDI): through the use of standardized building blocks metadata will not be subject to
      arbitrary and very diverse, individually preferred ways of describing data about data
      (=metadata). All the necessary information can be extracted easily from the standardized
      metadata-descriptions without having to study the data themselves and first understanding the
      individual way authors of metadata have set up their descriptions. Through standardization,
      working with metadata is thus made easy for authors and users. All in all, the potential of
      sharing and storing self-designed components and profiles for reuse by others facilitates
      flexible, but structured metadata building and search among various language resources.</para>
    <para>Another advantage of CMDI is the possibility of linking elements in components and
      profiles to the <ulink url="https://catalog.clarin.eu/isocat/interface/index.html">ISOcat
        concept registry</ulink>. This registry is a central framework for gathering concepts in
      various domains and has special profiles for metadata related categories. By creating links to
      this registry users searching for certain kinds of data in ISOcat will be enabled to find all
      data belonging to different authors, thanks to standardized metadata descriptions and to the
      central registry. It is thus highly recommended to browse through ISOcat and to create links
      to it when working with CMDI, which can be done from inside the Component Registry. </para>
    <para>The last significant CLARIN-related instrument to be mentioned here is the <ulink
        url="http://catalog.clarin.eu/vlo/">VLO</ulink> (Virtual Language Observatory). This website
      gives an overview of metadata from a certain amount of registries covering a large number of
      institutions which make use of CDMI. Additionally, all metadata which has been created with
      the help of CMDI is available in the several records provided by the institutions. This
      service facilitates the search for, and the exchange of, data with the help of metadata by
      researchers’ communities in the field.</para>
    <sect1>
      <title>
        <emphasis role="bold">Creating profiles and components in the Component Registry</emphasis>
      </title>
      <para>For building, searching and using profiles and components a tool has been developed,
        which is the Component Registry. The <ulink
          url="http://catalog.clarin.eu/ds/ComponentRegistry/">component registry</ulink> (and its
          <ulink url="http://www.clarin.eu/node/3223">manual</ulink>) can be found on the CLARIN
        website. </para>
      <para>This short introduction of CMDI will outline the most basic features for using the
        infrastructure.</para>
      <sect2>
        <title>Login</title>
        <para>To login to the Component Registry you have to choose one’s organization from the list
          or opt for "Clarin Guest Accounts". To log out simply end the browser session. </para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title> Features of the Component Registry</title>
        <para>The first way of using CMDI is browsing through registered components and profiles.
          The second way consists of editing and creating components or profiles.</para>
        <para>Registering and storing components or CMDI profiles are further functions of the
          component registry. </para>
        <para>To illustrate the workflow in the component registry please consult the following
            <xref linkend="figure_2"/>: </para>
        <para>
          <figure>
            <title id="figure_2">Workflow from CMDI to Arbil</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/Appendix_Component_CMDImanual_image0.2.png" width="100%"
                  scalefit="1" contentdepth="100%"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </para>
        <sect3>
          <title>Component Browser</title>
          <para>The start screen of the <ulink url="http://catalog.clarin.eu/ds/ComponentRegistry/#"
              >Component Registry</ulink> is called the component browser, which is the entry point
            for using other functions (editing and importing) (see <xref linkend="figure_3"/>).
            First, though, the user can browse for either profiles or components. Search-terms can
            be typed in a field at the top on the right to filter out non-matching items.
            Additionally the user can switch between public and (unpublished, private) user
            workspaces. For more information on individual profiles or components, one can select
            the entity in question and details will appear in the panel below. Such panel can be
            optionally displayed in an interactive default view (to explore structure more in depth)
            or in an xml-view of the actual component assessed. </para>
          <para>Right-clicking on items in the list leads to options such as downloading profiles or
            components as xml representations or downloading the respective xsd. The latter can be
            loaded into Arbil for usage before publication (see section ' <xref
              linkend="link_to_appendix"/>'), and suits further use by other tools within
            CLARIN.</para>
          <para>On the top-left of the Component Registry you will find three options: the first
            option (<emphasis role="bold">Create new</emphasis>) allows creating a new profile or
            component in a private workspace. If you choose the second (<emphasis role="bold">Edit
              as new</emphasis>), a selected item can be opened in the editor after authentication
            of the user, depending on whether it is a copy of a public space or an item in the
            users’ workspace. The last option (<emphasis role="bold">Import</emphasis>) leads to an
            import form, which will not be discussed in this chapter. </para>
          <para>
            <figure>
              <title id="figure_3"> Component Registry window and functions offered: The first red
                demarcation shows the option to choose between profiles and components (1). The
                second demarcation shows the option to choose for public or private space (2). The
                third demarcation highlights the filter option field (3).</title>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/Appendix_componentbrowser_Cmdimanual_image2.png"
                    contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>
          </para>
        </sect3>
        <sect3>
          <title>Component Editor</title>
          <para>With the help of the component editor the user can modify a profile and/or its
            components (see <xref linkend="figure_4"/>). You can access it - after having selected
            the profile to modify - via the option <emphasis role="bold">Edit as new</emphasis>
            mentioned above. A page like the one shown in the figure below will be shown.</para>
          <para>
            <figure>
              <title id="figure_4"> Component editor. The first red demarcation indicates where you
                find the main menu bar in the component editor (1). The second demarcation shows
                where information is found about whether a component or a profile is edited (2). The
                third one shows the option to add attributes (3). In the fourth demarcation the
                field for editing elements is stressed (4). The last highlights the option to choose
                from public or private space to drag existing components into the editor
                (5).</title>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/component_editor.png" contentdepth="100%" scalefit="1"
                    width="100%"/>
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>
          </para>
          <para>To reuse existing components (Edit (as new) –function) select an existing component
            from the list below, drag it over the editing panel. Here options will be highlighted
            where dropping the component is possible. If the component already exists, at this point
            a reference will be automatically generated to it. Be aware that components which you
            you have not published yet cannot be used by anyone else. Instead referenced components
            which you create and publish can be reused by others (when viewing profiles these
            components are marked by a blue frame in the list of the lower part of the screen). The
            green buttons indicate options for adding new components (“+component”, ”+element”,
            “+attribute”), so that newly created fields can be worked on. Up and down arrows allow
            to reorder elements and components.  </para>
          <para>The “save”-function can be used to submit and overwrite existing profiles or
            components in private workspaces. Existing profiles or components can be used as a basis
            for new profiles or components without overwriting the existing. In this case the user
            can apply “save as new” in their private workspaces and work on the profiles and
            components to adapt them to their needs. The function “publish in public space” is to
            submit a profile or component as a building-block accessible for others, finalizing the
            modeling phase of that particular profile or component since after publication, a
            profile or component cannot be changed anymore. To return to the component browser and
            discard changes, press “cancel”. </para>
          <para>For more detailed information about more elaborate editing processes (type, import,
            concept links, action links, comments and priority display) have a look at the <ulink
              url="http://tla.mpi.nl/cmdi-metadata/">CMDI metadata</ulink> page on the TLA website,
            the <ulink url="http://www.clarin.eu/node/3219">CLARIN website</ulink> - where you can
            access the <ulink url="http://www.clarin.eu/content/component-registry-documentation"
              >Component Registry Documentation</ulink> - or the extensive <ulink
              url="http://tla.mpi.nl/cmdi-metadata/">CMDI manual</ulink> of the TLA.</para>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
  </appendix>
</book>
